<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE ALGORITHM SYSTEM "https://cms.hivdb.org/prod/downloads/asi/ASI2.3.dtd">
<ALGORITHM>
  <ALGNAME>HIVDB</ALGNAME>
  <ALGVERSION>9.4</ALGVERSION>
  <ALGDATE>2022-12-07</ALGDATE>
  <DEFINITIONS>
    <GENE_DEFINITION>
      <NAME>CA</NAME>
      <DRUGCLASSLIST>CAI</DRUGCLASSLIST>
    </GENE_DEFINITION>
    <GENE_DEFINITION>
      <NAME>PR</NAME>
      <DRUGCLASSLIST>PI</DRUGCLASSLIST>
    </GENE_DEFINITION>
    <GENE_DEFINITION>
      <NAME>RT</NAME>
      <DRUGCLASSLIST>NRTI,NNRTI</DRUGCLASSLIST>
    </GENE_DEFINITION>
    <GENE_DEFINITION>
      <NAME>IN</NAME>
      <DRUGCLASSLIST>INSTI</DRUGCLASSLIST>
    </GENE_DEFINITION>
    <LEVEL_DEFINITION>
      <ORDER>1</ORDER>
      <ORIGINAL>Susceptible</ORIGINAL>
      <SIR>S</SIR>
    </LEVEL_DEFINITION>
    <LEVEL_DEFINITION>
      <ORDER>2</ORDER>
      <ORIGINAL>Potential Low-Level Resistance</ORIGINAL>
      <SIR>S</SIR>
    </LEVEL_DEFINITION>
    <LEVEL_DEFINITION>
      <ORDER>3</ORDER>
      <ORIGINAL>Low-Level Resistance</ORIGINAL>
      <SIR>I</SIR>
    </LEVEL_DEFINITION>
    <LEVEL_DEFINITION>
      <ORDER>4</ORDER>
      <ORIGINAL>Intermediate Resistance</ORIGINAL>
      <SIR>I</SIR>
    </LEVEL_DEFINITION>
    <LEVEL_DEFINITION>
      <ORDER>5</ORDER>
      <ORIGINAL>High-Level Resistance</ORIGINAL>
      <SIR>R</SIR>
    </LEVEL_DEFINITION>
    <DRUGCLASS>
      <NAME>NRTI</NAME>
      <DRUGLIST>ABC,AZT,D4T,DDI,FTC,3TC,TDF</DRUGLIST>
    </DRUGCLASS>
    <DRUGCLASS>
      <NAME>NNRTI</NAME>
      <DRUGLIST>DOR,EFV,ETR,NVP,RPV</DRUGLIST>
    </DRUGCLASS>
    <DRUGCLASS>
      <NAME>PI</NAME>
      <DRUGLIST>ATV/r,DRV/r,FPV/r,IDV/r,LPV/r,NFV,SQV/r,TPV/r</DRUGLIST>
    </DRUGCLASS>
    <DRUGCLASS>
      <NAME>INSTI</NAME>
      <DRUGLIST>BIC,CAB,DTG,EVG,RAL</DRUGLIST>
    </DRUGCLASS>
    <DRUGCLASS>
      <NAME>CAI</NAME>
      <DRUGLIST>LEN</DRUGLIST>
    </DRUGCLASS>
    <GLOBALRANGE><![CDATA[(-INF TO 9 => 1,  10 TO 14 => 2,  15 TO 29 => 3,  30 TO 59 => 4,  60 TO INF => 5)]]></GLOBALRANGE>
    <DEFAULT_LEVEL>1</DEFAULT_LEVEL>
    <COMMENT_DEFINITIONS>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="CA105TSE">
        <!--<DATE>2022-12-07</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>CAI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[A105T has been selected in 2 patients receiving LEN in combination with M66I. Alone it is associated with 3-fold reduced LEN susceptibility and an RC of ~60%. A105E was selected in vitro by GS-CA1. It is associated with ~4-fold reduced LEN susceptibility. A105S has been reported as a subdominant variant in one patient receiving LEN. Its effect on susceptibility has not been reported.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="CA107NS">
        <!--<DATE>2022-12-07</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>CAI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[T107N has been selected in vitro by LEN in combination with Q67H. Alone it is associated with 4-fold reduced LEN susceptibility. In combination with Q67H, it is associated with ~90-fold reduced LEN susceptibility. T107A has been reported in combination with M66I in 1 patient receiving LEN. The combination was associated with 240-fold reduced LEN susceptibility.  Its effect on susceptibility alone has not been reported. T107S is a common polymorphism that occurs in previously untreated persons.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="CA56I">
        <!--<DATE>2022-12-07</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>CAI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[L56I has been selected in vitro by LEN. It is associated with ~200-fold reduced LEN susceptibility. It has an RC of 3%-9%.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="CA57S">
        <!--<DATE>2022-12-07</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>CAI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[N57S had been selected in vitro by GS-CA1 and is associated with ~25-fold reduced GS-CA1 susceptibility.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="CA66I">
        <!--<DATE>2022-12-07</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>CAI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[M66I has been selected in vitro by LEN. It is associated with >1000-fold reduced LEN susceptibility. It has an RC of 1%-6%. It occurred in 6 patients in the CAPELLA study usually in combination with other mutations.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="CA67H">
        <!--<DATE>2022-12-07</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>CAI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[Q67H has been selected in vitro by LEN. It is associated with ~5-fold reduced LEN susceptibility and an RC of ~60%. Q67H+K70R were selected in 2 patients receiving LEN. The combination is associated with 15-20-fold reduced LEN susceptibility. Q67Y, Q67N, and Q67K have been reported in vitro or in vivo as subdominant variants. Q67Y has been selected in vitro by GS-CA1. It is associated with 10-20-fold reduced LEN acitivity. ]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="CA70NHRS">
        <!--<DATE>2022-12-07</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>CAI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[K70R has been selected in vitro by LEN in combination with Q67H. Q67H+K70R has been selected in 2 patients receiving LEN. Alone K70R is associated with 1.2 fold reduced susceptibility. The combination of Q67H+K70R is associated with 15-20-fold reduced LEN susceptibility. K70H has been selected in 1 patient receiving LEN. It is associated with ~100-fold reduced susceptibility and an RC of ~10%. K70S has been selected in 1 patient receiving LEN. Its effect on susceptibility has not been repored. K70N has been associated with ~20-fold reduced LEN susceptibility and an RC of ~1%. ]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="CA74DS">
        <!--<DATE>2022-12-07</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>CAI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[N74D has been selected in vitro by LEN both alone and in combination with Q67H. Alone, it is associated with ~20-fold reduced LEN susceptibility and an RC of ~50%. In combination with Q67H, it is associated with >1000 reduced LEN susceptibility. N74D occurred in 1 patient in combination with M66I. N74S has been selected in vitro by LEN in combination with Q67H. In combination with Q67H, it is associated with 20-fold reduced susceptibility.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="CABIntermediate">
        <!--<DATE>2021-03-01</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[This virus is predicted to have intermediate-level reduced susceptibility to CAB. The use of the combination of CAB/RPV should be considered to be contraindicated.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="CABLow">
        <!--<DATE>2021-03-01</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[This virus is predicted to have low-level reduced susceptibility to CAB. The use of the combination of CAB/RPV should be considered to be relatively contraindicated.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="DTGHigh">
        <!--<DATE>2017-02-28</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[There is evidence for high-level DTG resistance. If DTG is used, it should be administered twice daily.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="DTGIntermediate">
        <!--<DATE>2017-02-28</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[There is evidence for intermediate DTG resistance. If DTG is used, it should be administered twice daily.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="DTGLow">
        <!--<DATE>2017-02-28</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[There is evidence for low-level DTG resistance. If DTG is used, it should be administered twice daily.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN118ACDEFHIKLMNPQSTVWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-23</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[G118R is a nonpolymorphic mutation reported in a significant proportion of persons with VF and emergent HIVDR in persons receiving a DTG-containing regimen. It has occasionally been reported in persons receiving other INSTIs. It is associated with 5-10-fold reduced susceptibility to RAL, EVG, DTG and CAB, and 2-3 fold reduced susceptibility to BIC. $listMutsIn{118(NOT R)} is an unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN118R">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-23</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[G118R is a nonpolymorphic mutation reported in a significant proportion of persons with VF and emergent HIVDR in persons receiving a DTG-containing regimen. It has occasionally been reported in persons receiving other INSTIs. It is associated with 5-10-fold reduced susceptibility to RAL, EVG, DTG and CAB, and 2-3 fold reduced susceptibility to BIC.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN119R">
        <!--<DATE>2018-07-18</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[S119R is a polymorphic mutation that is weakly selected by INSTIs usually in combination with several major INSTI-associated DRMs. Alone, it has little, if any effect, on INSTI susceptibility.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN121ADEGHIKLMNPQRSTVWid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-23</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[F121Y is a rare nonpolymorphic mutation selected primarily by RAL. It is associated with >10-fold reduced susceptibility to RAL but has minimal if any effect on susceptibility to CAB, DTG, and BIC. F121C is an extremely rare mutation. Preliminary data suggests it may confers high level phenotypic resistance to RAL, EVG, and possibly CAB. $listMutsIn{121(NOT Y)} is an unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN121C">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-23</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[F121C is an extremely rare mutation. Preliminary data suggests it may confers high level phenotypic resistance to RAL, EVG, and possibly CAB.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN121Y">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-23</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[F121Y is a rare nonpolymorphic mutation selected primarily by RAL. It is associated with >10-fold reduced susceptibility to RAL but has minimal if any effect on susceptibility to CAB, DTG, and BIC.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN128T">
        <!--<DATE>2016-12-09</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[A128T is a relatively nonpolymorphic possible INSTI-selected mutation, which does not appear to reduce INSTI susceptibility.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN138CFGHILMNPQRSVWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-23</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[E138K/A/T are common nonpolymorphic accessory resistance mutations selected in patients receiving RAL, EVG, CAB, and DTG. Alone they do not reduce INSTI susceptibility. However, they contribute to reduced susceptibility in combination with other mutations particularly those at position 148. E138D is a polymorphism that occurs in 1% to 2% of viruses from INSTI-naive patients. It does not appear to be selected by INSTIs or to reduce INSTI susceptibility. $listMutsIn{138(NOT KATD)} is an unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN138D">
        <!--<DATE>2016-12-09</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[E138D is a polymorphism that occurs in 1% to 2% of viruses from INSTI-naive patients. It does not appear to be selected by INSTIs or to reduce INSTI susceptibility.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN138KAT">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-23</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[E138K/A/T are common nonpolymorphic accessory resistance mutations selected in patients receiving RAL, EVG, CAB, and DTG. Alone they do not reduce INSTI susceptibility. However, they contribute to reduced susceptibility in combination with other mutations particularly those at position 148.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN140DEFHIKLMNPQTVWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-23</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[G140S/A/C are non-polymorphic mutations that usually occur with Q148 mutations. Alone, they have minimal effects on INSTI susceptibility. However, in combination with Q148 mutations they are associated with high-level resistance to RAL and EVG and intermediate reductions in DTG and BIC susceptibility. G140R is a nonpolymorphic mutation reported in n macaques receiving CAB pre-exposure prophylaxis and in a person receiving simplification therapy with RPV/CAB. It can reduce CAB susceptibility up to 7-fold. $listMutsIn{140(NOT SACR)} is an unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN140R">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-23</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[G140R is a nonpolymorphic mutation reported in n macaques receiving CAB pre-exposure prophylaxis and in a person receiving simplification therapy with RPV/CAB. It can reduce CAB susceptibility up to 7-fold.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN140SAC">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-23</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[G140S/A/C are non-polymorphic mutations that usually occur with Q148 mutations. Alone, they have minimal effects on INSTI susceptibility. However, in combination with Q148 mutations they are associated with high-level resistance to RAL and EVG and intermediate reductions in DTG and BIC susceptibility.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN143CRH">
        <!--<DATE>2021-02-22</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[Y143C/R/H are non-polymorphic mutations associated with high-level RAL resistance. Alone, they have minimal effects on EVG susceptibility. However, they are associated with intermediate reductions in EVG susceptibility when they occur in combination with one or more accessory INSTI-resistance mutations. Y143 mutations do not reduce susceptibility to DTG, BIC, or CAB.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN143DEFILMNPQTVWid">
        <!--<DATE>2021-02-22</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[Y143C/R/H are non-polymorphic mutations associated with high-level RAL resistance. Alone, they have minimal effects on EVG susceptibility. However, they are associated with intermediate reductions in EVG susceptibility when they occur in combination with one or more accessory INSTI-resistance mutations. Y143 mutations do not reduce susceptibility to DTG, BIC, or CAB. $listMutsIn{143(NOT CRHKGSA)} is an unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN143KGSA">
        <!--<DATE>2016-12-09</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[Y143K/G/S/A are rare mutations that cause intermediate reductions in RAL susceptibility. When they occur in combination with other accessory mutations, they may also cause low-level reductions in EVG susceptibility.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN145ACDEFGHIKLMNQRTVWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2021-02-22</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[P145S is a rare non-polymorphic mutation selected in vitro by EVG and rarely in patients receiving EVG. It causes high-level resistance to EVG but not to any other INSTI. $listMutsIn{145(NOT S)} is an unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN145S">
        <!--<DATE>2021-02-22</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[P145S is a rare non-polymorphic mutation selected in vitro by EVG and rarely in patients receiving EVG. It causes high-level resistance to EVG but not to any other INSTI.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN146ACDEFGHIKLMNRSTVWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-23</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[Q146P/R/L are rare mutations that have been selected in vitro by EVG, DTG, BIC, and CAB. Q146P/L have been associated with 5-15-fold reduced EVG susceptibility but not with reduced susceptibility to other INSTIs. $listMutsIn{146(NOT P)} is an unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN146PRL">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-23</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[Q146P/R/L are rare mutations that have been selected in vitro by EVG, DTG, BIC, and CAB. Q146P/L have been associated with 5-15-fold reduced EVG susceptibility but not with reduced susceptibility to other INSTIs.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN147ACDEFHIKLMNPQRTVWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-23</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[S147G is a nonpolymorphic mutation selected in patients receiving RAL, EVG, and DTG. Alone it reduces EVG susceptibility about 5-fold. $listMutsIn{147(NOT G)} is an unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN147G">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-23</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[S147G is a nonpolymorphic mutation selected in patients receiving RAL, EVG, and DTG. Alone it reduces EVG susceptibility about 5-fold.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN148ACDEFGILMPSTVWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-23</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[Q148H/K/R are nonpolymorphic mutations reported in persons receiving RAL, EVG, CAB, and DTG. They nearly always occur in combination with G140A/S or E138K. In this setting they are associated with near complete resistance to RAL and EVG, high-levels of reduction in CAB susceptibility, and low-to-intermediate reductions in DTG and BIC susceptibility. Q148N is a very rare INSTI-selected mutation that causes ~3-fold reduced EVG susceptibility and may represent a reversion from Q148H or Q148K. $listMutsIn{148(NOT HKRN)} is an unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN148HKR">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-23</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[Q148H/K/R are nonpolymorphic mutations reported in persons receiving RAL, EVG, CAB, and DTG. They nearly always occur in combination with G140A/S or E138K. In this setting they are associated with near complete resistance to RAL and EVG, high-levels of reduction in CAB susceptibility, and low-to-intermediate reductions in DTG and BIC susceptibility.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN148N">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-23</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[Q148N is a very rare INSTI-selected mutation that causes ~3-fold reduced EVG susceptibility and may represent a reversion from Q148H or Q148K.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN149A">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-23</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[G149A is an accessory nonpolymorphic mutation that has been reported primarily in combination with Q148 mutations. It appears to have no effect by itself but in combination with mutations at positions 140 and 148, it leads to contributes reduced susceptibility to DTG, CAB, and BIC.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN151A">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-23</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[V151A is an extremely rare mutation associated with minimally reduced susceptibility to RAL and EVG.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN151CDEFGHKMNPQRSTWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-23</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[V151I is an accessory INSTI selected mutation that occurs in 1% to 3% of viruses from ART-naive persons depending on subtype. Alone, it appears to have little or no effect on INSTI susceptibility. V151L is an extremely rare mutation that reduces susceptibility to RAL and EVG by 15 to 20-fold and to CAB and DTG by about 3-fold. V151A is an extremely rare mutation associated with minimally reduced susceptibility to RAL and EVG. $listMutsIn{151(NOT IAL)} is an unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN151I">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-23</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[V151I is an accessory INSTI selected mutation that occurs in 1% to 3% of viruses from ART-naive persons depending on subtype. Alone, it appears to have little or no effect on INSTI susceptibility.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN151L">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-23</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[V151L is an extremely rare mutation that reduces susceptibility to RAL and EVG by 15 to 20-fold and to CAB and DTG by about 3-fold.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN153ACDEGHIKLMNPQRTVWid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-23</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[S153Y/F are very rare mutations selected in vitro by EVG, DTG, BIC, and CAB. Alone they reduce EVG susceptibility about 5-fold and DTG, CAB, and BIC susceptibility about 2-fold. S153A is a rare mutation that alone does not appear to reduce INSTI susceptibility. $listMutsIn{153(NOT YF)} is an unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN153YFA">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-23</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[S153Y/F are very rare mutations selected in vitro by EVG, DTG, BIC, and CAB. Alone they reduce EVG susceptibility about 5-fold and DTG, CAB, and BIC susceptibility about 2-fold. S153A is a rare mutation that alone does not appear to reduce INSTI susceptibility.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN155ACDEFGIKLMPQRVWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-23</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[N155H is a common nonpolymorphic INSTI-resistance mutations. It has been reported in a high proportion of persons developing VF and HIVDR while receiving RAL, EVG, DTG, and CAB. Alone, it reduces RAL and EVG susceptibility about 10 and 30-fold, respectively.  It has minimal effect on susceptibility to DTG, BIC, and CAB. N155S/T are extremely rare nonpolymorphic mutations that reduce RAL and EVG susceptibility about 5-fold and greater than 30-fold respectively but have little effect on CAB, DTG, and BIC.  $listMutsIn{155(NOT HST)} is an unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN155H">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-23</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[N155H is a common nonpolymorphic INSTI-resistance mutations. It has been reported in a high proportion of persons developing VF and HIVDR while receiving RAL, EVG, DTG, and CAB. Alone, it reduces RAL and EVG susceptibility about 10 and 30-fold, respectively.  It has minimal effect on susceptibility to DTG, BIC, and CAB.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN155ST">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-23</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[N155S/T are extremely rare nonpolymorphic mutations that reduce RAL and EVG susceptibility about 5-fold and greater than 30-fold respectively but have little effect on CAB, DTG, and BIC.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN157Q">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-23</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[E157Q is a polymorphic mutation selected in persons receiving RAL and EVG. It appears to have little effect on INSTI susceptibility.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN163RK">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-23</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[G163R/K are nonpolymorphic in all subtypes except subtype F. They are accessory resistance mutations as they usually occur in combination with other INSTI-resistance mutations particularly N155H.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN230N">
        <!--<DATE>2016-12-09</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[S230N is a polymorphism that is not associated with reduced INSTI susceptibility.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN230R">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-23</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[S230R is a nonpolymorphic INSTI-selected mutation that primarily occurs in combination with other INSTI-resistance mutations. By itself, it appears to have minimal effect on susceptibility to available INSTIs.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN232N">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-23</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[D232N is a common nonpolymorphic accessory mutation selected in persons receiving RAL and EVG. Alone, it has little effect on INSTI susceptibility.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN263ACDEFGHILMNPQSTVWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-23</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[R263K is a nonpolymorphic mutation selected in vitro by EVG, DTG, BIC, and CAB. It occurs in a high proportion of persons who develop VF and emergent HIVDR while receiving DTG. Alone, it reduces DTG, BIC, and CAB susceptibility about 2-fold. $listMutsIn{263(NOT K)} is an unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN263K">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-23</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[R263K is a nonpolymorphic mutation selected in vitro by EVG, DTG, BIC, and CAB. It occurs in a high proportion of persons who develop VF and emergent HIVDR while receiving DTG. Alone, it reduces DTG, BIC, and CAB susceptibility about 2-fold.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN49G">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-23</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[A49G is a rare nonpolymorphic accessory INSTI-selected mutation with uncertain effects on INSTI susceptibility.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN50I">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-23</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[M50I is a highly polymorphic mutation, which has a prevalence of 3% to 34% in INSTI-naïve persons depending on subtype. It has been selected in vitro by DTG and BIC in combination with R263K. It may contribute to reduced DTG and CAB susceptibility in combination with R263K.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN51ACDEFGIKLMNPQRSTVWid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-23</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[H51Y is an uncommon nonpolymorphic accessory mutation selected in vitro by EVG, DTG, and CAB. Alone, it has minimal if any effect on INSTI susceptibility. $listMutsIn{51(NOT Y)} is an unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN51Y">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-23</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[H51Y is an uncommon nonpolymorphic accessory mutation selected in vitro by EVG, DTG, and CAB. Alone, it has minimal if any effect on INSTI susceptibility.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN66AI">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-23</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[T66A/I are non-polymorphic mutations selected in persons receiving EVG, RAL, and DTG usually in combination with other INSTI-resistance mutations. They cause moderate reductions in EVG susceptibility but do not appear to reduce susceptibility to other INSTIs.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN66CDEFGHLMNPQRSVWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-23</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[T66A/I are non-polymorphic mutations selected in persons receiving EVG, RAL, and DTG usually in combination with other INSTI-resistance mutations. They cause moderate reductions in EVG susceptibility but do not appear to reduce susceptibility to other INSTIs. T66K is an uncommon non-polymorphic INSTI-selected mutation. It is associated with high-level EVG resistance, intermediate/high-level RAL resistance, and low-level DTG and CAB resistance. Its effect on BIC is not known. $listMutsIn{66(NOT IAK)} is an unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN66K">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-23</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[T66K is an uncommon non-polymorphic INSTI-selected mutation. It is associated with high-level EVG resistance, intermediate/high-level RAL resistance, and low-level DTG and CAB resistance. Its effect on BIC is not known.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN74F">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-23</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[L74F is an extremely rare nonpolymorphic mutation which contributes to reduced INSTI susceptibility when it occurs with other INSTI-resistance mutations.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN74I">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-23</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[L74I is a highly polymorphic mutation with a prevalence of 3% to 30% depending on subtype. It is the consensus amino acid in subtype A viruses belonging to the A6 clade. It does not appear to be selected by any of the INSTIs or to reduce their susceptibility.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN74M">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-23</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[L74M is a common polymorphic INSTI-resistance mutation. It has a prevalence between 1% and 5% among INSTI-naïve persons depending on subtype. It appears to be selected by each of the INSTIs. Alone it does not reduce INSTI susceptibility. However, in combination with other INSTI-resistance mutations, it contributes reduced susceptibility to each of the INSTIs.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN92ACDFHIKLMNPRSTWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-23</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[E92Q is a common non-polymorphic mutation selected in persons receiving RAL and EVG. It reduces RAL susceptibility 5 to 10-fold and EVG susceptibility ~30-fold. It does not reduce susceptibility to BIC, CAB, and DTG. E92G/V are rare nonpolymorphic mutations that reduce EVG susceptibility >=10-fold but do not appear to reduce susceptibility to other INSTIs. $listMutsIn{92(NOT GQV)} is an unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN92GV">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-23</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[E92G/V are rare nonpolymorphic mutations that reduce EVG susceptibility >=10-fold but do not appear to reduce susceptibility to other INSTIs.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN92Q">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-23</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[E92Q is a common non-polymorphic mutation selected in persons receiving RAL and EVG. It reduces RAL susceptibility 5 to 10-fold and EVG susceptibility ~30-fold. It does not reduce susceptibility to BIC, CAB, and DTG.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN95K">
        <!--<DATE>2016-12-09</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[Q95K is a non-polymorphic INSTI-selected mutation. Alone, it has little if any effect on INSTI susceptibility.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="IN97A">
        <!--<DATE>2021-02-22</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>INSTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[T97A is a polymorphic INSTI-selected mutation that, depending on subtype, occurs in 1% to 5% of viruses from untreated persons. Alone, it has minimal effects on INSTI susceptibility but in combination with other major resistance mutations, it synergistically reduces susceptibility to each of the INSTIs.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="DRVHigh">
        <!--<DATE>2017-03-02</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[There is evidence for high-level DRV resistance. If DRV is administered it should be used twice daily.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="DRVHighAndTPVIntermediate">
        <!--<DATE>2017-02-28</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[There is high-level DRV resistance and intermediate TPV resistance. Phenotypic testing and/or expert consultation may be useful. To see the precise TPV report re-run the program after adding TPV to the results being displayed.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="DRVHighAndTPVLow">
        <!--<DATE>2017-02-28</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[There is high-level DRV resistance and low-level TPV resistance. Phenotypic testing and/or expert consultation may be useful. To see the precise TPV report re-run the program after adding TPV to the results being displayed.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="DRVHighAndTPVPotentialLow">
        <!--<DATE>2017-03-02</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[There is high-level DRV resistance and potential low-level TPV resistance. Phenotypic testing and/or expert consultation may be useful. To see the precise TPV report re-run the program after adding TPV to the results being displayed.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="DRVHighAndTPVSusceptible">
        <!--<DATE>2017-03-02</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[There is high-level DRV resistance and TPV susceptibility. Phenotypic testing and/or expert consultation may be useful. To see the precise TPV report re-run the program after adding TPV to the results being displayed.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="DRVIntermediate">
        <!--<DATE>2017-03-02</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[There is evidence for intermediate DRV resistance. If DRV is administered it should be used twice daily.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="DRVLow">
        <!--<DATE>2017-03-02</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[There is evidence for low-level DRV resistance. If DRV is administered it should be used twice daily.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR10ACDEGHKMNPQSTWid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[L10F is a common non-polymorphic, PI-selected accessory mutation associated with reduced in vitro susceptibility to LPV and DRV. L10I/V are polymorphic, PI-selected accessory mutations that increase the replication of viruses with other PI-resistance mutations. L10R/Y are rare, non-polymorphic PI-selected mutations. Their effects on PI susceptibility have not been well studied. $listMutsIn{10(NOT FIVRY)} is a highly unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR10F">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[L10F is a common non-polymorphic, PI-selected accessory mutation associated with reduced in vitro susceptibility to LPV and DRV.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR10IV">
        <!--<DATE>2016-12-09</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[L10I/V are polymorphic, PI-selected accessory mutations that increase the replication of viruses with other PI-resistance mutations.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR10RY">
        <!--<DATE>2016-12-09</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[L10R/Y are rare, non-polymorphic PI-selected mutations. Their effects on PI susceptibility have not been well studied.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR11IL">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[V11I/L are relatively non-polymorphic accessory mutation selected in persons receiving DRV. V11L is a nonpolymorphic PI-selected mutation associated with reduced in vitro DRV  susceptibility when it occurs in combination with other PI-resistance mutations.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR20I">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[K20I is the consensus amino acid in subtype G and CRF02_AG. In subtypes B and C, K20I is a PI-selected mutation of uncertain effects on currently used PIs.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR20MV">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[K20M/V are uncommonrelatively non-polymorphic PI-selected mutations that have not been well studied.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR20R">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[K20R is a highly polymorphic PI-selected accessory mutation that increases replication fitness in viruses with PI-resistance mutations.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR20T">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[K20T is a non-polymorphic accessory PI-selected mutation associated with reduced susceptibility to ATV and LPV.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR23I">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[L23I is an uncommon non-polymorphic mutation selected primarily by NFV. It appears to have minimal if any effects on the susceptibility to other PIs.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR24ACDEGHKNPQRSTVWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[L24I is a non-polymorphic mutation selected by IDV and LPV. It contributes reduced susceptibility to ATV and LPV. L24F/M are uncommon non-polymorphic PI-selected mutations. L24F has a susceptibility profile similar to L24I. $listMutsIn{24(NOT FIM)} is a highly unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR24FM">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[L24I is a non-polymorphic mutation selected by IDV and LPV. It contributes reduced susceptibility to ATV and LPV. L24F/M are uncommon non-polymorphic PI-selected mutations. L24F has a susceptibility profile similar to L24I.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR24I">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[L24I is a non-polymorphic mutation selected by IDV and LPV. It contributes reduced susceptibility to ATV and LPV.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR30ACEFGHIKLMPQRSTVWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[D30N is a non-polymorphic mutation NFV-selected mutation that causes high-level resistance to NFV but not to other PIs. $listMutsIn{30(NOT N)} is a highly unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR30N">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[D30N is a non-polymorphic mutation NFV-selected mutation that causes high-level resistance to NFV but not to other PIs.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR32ACDEFGHKLMNPQRSTWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[V32I is a non-polymorphic mutation selected by LPV, ATV, and DRV which is associated with reduced susceptibility to each of these PIs. $listMutsIn{32(NOT I)} is a highly unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR32I">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[V32I is a non-polymorphic mutation selected by LPV, ATV, and DRV which is associated with reduced susceptibility to each of these PIs.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR33-41i">
        <!--<DATE>2018-07-18</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[Insertions between positions 33 and 41 do not appear to be selected by PIs or to reduce PI susceptibility.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR33F">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[L33F is a relatively non-polymorphic accessory mutation selected by each of the PIs. In combination with other PI-resistance mutations, it is associated with reduced susceptibility to LPV, ATV, and DOR.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR33IV">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[L33I/V are minimally polymorphic mutations that do not appear to be selected by PIs or to reduce their susceptibility.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR43T">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[K43T is a nonpolymorphic accessory mutation selected by ATV and LPV. Its phenotypic effect on currently used PIs is uncertain.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR46ACDEFGHKNPQRSTWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2016-12-09</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[M46I/L are relatively non-polymorphic PI-selected mutations. In combination with other PI-resistance mutations, they are associated with reduced susceptibility to each of the PIs except DRV. $listMutsIn{46(NOT ILV)} is a highly unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR46IL">
        <!--<DATE>2016-12-09</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[M46I/L are relatively non-polymorphic PI-selected mutations. In combination with other PI-resistance mutations, they are associated with reduced susceptibility to each of the PIs except DRV.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR46V">
        <!--<DATE>2016-12-09</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[M46I/L are relatively non-polymorphic PI-selected mutations. In combination with other PI-resistance mutations, they are associated with reduced susceptibility to each of the PIs except DRV. M46V is a rare non-polymorphic PI-selected mutation that has not been well studied.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR47A">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[I47A is a non-polymorphic mutation selected by LPV. It usually occurs in combination with V32I and in this context it confers high-level resistance to LPV and low-level resistance to DRV.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR47CDEFGHKLMNPQRSTWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[I47V is a non-polymorphic PI-selected mutation associated with reduced susceptibility to LPV and DRV. $listMutsIn{47(NOT AV)} is a highly unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR47V">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[I47V is a non-polymorphic PI-selected mutation associated with reduced susceptibility to LPV and DRV.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR48ASTQL">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[G48V is a nonpolymorphic mutation selected by SQV and less often by IDV and LPV. It confers intermediate resistance to ATV but has little if any effect on LPV susceptibility. G48M is an uncommon 2-base-pair nonpolymorphic substrate-cleft mutation nearly always selected in viruses with multiple PI-resistance mutations. It has a resistance profile similar to G48V. G48A/S/T/Q/L are extremely rare nonpolymorphic PI-selected mutations nearly always selected in viruses with multiple PI-resistance mutations.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR48CDEFHIKNPRWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[G48V is a nonpolymorphic mutation selected by SQV and less often by IDV and LPV. It confers intermediate resistance to ATV but has little if any effect on LPV susceptibility. G48M is an uncommon 2-base-pair nonpolymorphic substrate-cleft mutation nearly always selected in viruses with multiple PI-resistance mutations. It has a resistance profile similar to G48V. G48A/S/T/Q/L are extremely rare nonpolymorphic PI-selected mutations nearly always selected in viruses with multiple PI-resistance mutations. $listMutsIn{48(NOT VMALSTQL)} is a highly unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR48M">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[G48V is a nonpolymorphic mutation selected by SQV and less often by IDV and LPV. It confers intermediate resistance to ATV but has little if any effect on LPV susceptibility. G48M is an uncommon 2-base-pair nonpolymorphic substrate-cleft mutation nearly always selected in viruses with multiple PI-resistance mutations. It has a resistance profile similar to G48V.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR48V">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[G48V is a nonpolymorphic mutation selected by SQV and less often by IDV and LPV. It confers intermediate resistance to ATV but has little if any effect on LPV susceptibility.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR50ACDEFGHKMNPQRSTWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[I50V is a nonpolymorphic mutation selected by FPV, LPV and DRV. It reduces susceptibility to LPV and DRV. I50L is a non-polymorphic mutation selected by ATV. It causes high-level resistance to ATV and increases susceptibility to LPV and DRV. $listMutsIn{50(NOT LV)} is a highly unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR50L">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[I50L is a non-polymorphic mutation selected by ATV. It causes high-level resistance to ATV and increases susceptibility to LPV and DRV.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR50V">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[I50V is a nonpolymorphic mutation selected by FPV, LPV and DRV. It reduces susceptibility to LPV and DRV.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR53LY">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[F53L is a nonpolymorphic accessory mutation selected primarily by SQV, IDV, ATV and LPV. In combination with other mutations, It is associated with reduced susceptibility to ATV and possibly LPV. F53Y is an uncommon nonpolymorphic accessory PI-selected mutation that has not been well studied.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR54ATS">
        <!--<DATE>2016-12-09</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[I54A/T/S are non-polymorphic PI-selected mutations that occur almost exclusively in viruses with multiple PI-resistance mutations. I54A/T/S are associated with reduced susceptibility to each of the PIs except DRV.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR54CDEFGHKNPQRWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[I54V is a non-polymorphic PI-selected mutation that contributes reduced susceptibility to each of the PIs except DRV. I54A/T/S are non-polymorphic PI-selected mutations that occur almost exclusively in viruses with multiple PI-resistance mutations. I54A/T/S are associated with reduced susceptibility to each of the PIs except DRV. I54M/L are non-polymorphic mutations selected primarily by FPV and DRV. I54M/L reduce susceptibility to LPV, ATV, and DRV. $listMutsIn{54(NOT ALMSTV)} is a highly unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR54LM">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[I54M/L are non-polymorphic mutations selected primarily by FPV and DRV. I54M/L reduce susceptibility to LPV, ATV, and DRV.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR54V">
        <!--<DATE>2016-12-09</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[I54V is a non-polymorphic PI-selected mutation that contributes reduced susceptibility to each of the PIs except DRV.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR58E">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[Q58E is a minimally polymorphic accessory mutation selected by each of the PIs except DRV. In combination with other PI-resistance mutations, it may contribute to low-level ATV resistance.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR71IL">
        <!--<DATE>2016-12-09</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[A71I/L are non-polymorphic, PI-selected accessory mutations that appear to increase the replication of viruses with other PI-resistance mutations.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR71TV">
        <!--<DATE>2016-12-09</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[A71V/T are polymorphic, PI-selected accessory mutations that increase the replication of viruses with other PI-resistance mutations.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR73EFHIKLMNPQRWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[G73S/T/C/A are common non-polymorphic accessory mutations selected primarily by most PIs. They are associated with minimally reduced susceptibility to each of the PIs. $listMutsIn{73(NOT ACDSTV)} is an unusual mutation at this position that has not been well studied.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR73STCA">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[G73S/T/C/A are common non-polymorphic accessory mutations selected primarily by most PIs. They are associated with minimally reduced susceptibility to each of the PIs.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR74P">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[T74P is a nonpolymorphic PI-selected accessory mutation that occurs primarily in viruses from persons who have received multiple PIs. In combination with other mutations, It is associated with reduced susceptibility to ATV and DRV.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR74S">
        <!--<DATE>2016-12-09</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[T74S is a PI-selected accessory mutation that is polymorphic in most non-B subtypes.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR76ACDEFGHIKMNPQRSTWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[L76V is a non-polymorphic mutation selected by IDV, LPV and DRV and reduces susceptibility to LPV and DRV. $listMutsIn{76(NOT V)} is a highly unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR76V">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[L76V is a non-polymorphic mutation selected by IDV, LPV and DRV and reduces susceptibility to LPV and DRV.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR82A">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[V82A is a non-polymorphic mutation selected primarily by IDV and LPV. It is associated with reduced susceptibility to LPV and to a lesser extent ATV. It increases DRV susceptibility.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR82C">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[V82C is an uncommon nonpolymorphic 2-base-pair PI-selected mutation that occurs in viruses with multiple PI-resistance mutations. Its effect on PI susceptibility has not been well studied.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR82DEGHKNPQRWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[V82A is a non-polymorphic mutation selected primarily by IDV and LPV. It is associated with reduced susceptibility to LPV and to a lesser extent ATV. It increases DRV susceptibility. V82T/S are nonpolymorphic mutations selected primarily by IDV and LPV. They are associated with reduced susceptibility to LPV and ATV, and increased susceptibility to DRV. V82F is a nonpolymorphic mutation selected primarily by IDV and LPV.  It reduces LPV and DRV susceptibility. V82C is an uncommon nonpolymorphic 2-base-pair PI-selected mutation that occurs in viruses with multiple PI-resistance mutations. Its effect on PI susceptibility has not been well studied. V82M is an uncommon nonpolymorphic PI-selected mutation. Its effect on currently used PIs is not well defined. $listMutsIn{82(NOT ATIFLMSC)} is a highly unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR82F">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[V82F is a nonpolymorphic mutation selected primarily by IDV and LPV.  It reduces LPV and DRV susceptibility.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR82I">
        <!--<DATE>2016-12-09</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[V82I is a highly polymorphic mutation that is not selected by PIs. It is the consensus amino acid in subtype G viruses.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR82L">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[V82L is a rare nonpolymorphic mutation selected primarily by TPV. Its effect on other PIs is not well characterized.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR82M">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[V82M is an uncommon nonpolymorphic PI-selected mutation. Its effect on currently used PIs is not well defined.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR82TS">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[V82T/S are nonpolymorphic mutations selected primarily by IDV and LPV. They are associated with reduced susceptibility to LPV and ATV, and increased susceptibility to DRV.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR83D">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[N83D is a nonpolymorphic PI-selected accessory mutation which possibly contributes to reduced ATV susceptibility in combination with other PI-resistance mutations.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR84AC">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[I84A/C are extremely rare non-polymorphic mutations selected primarily by SQV. I84A is associated with markedly reduced susceptibility to each of the PIs. I84C has a less-marked effect on PI susceptibility compared with I84A.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR84DEFGHKLMNPQRSTWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[I84V is a nonpolymorphic substrate-cleft mutation selected by each of the PIs. I84V reduces susceptibility to LPV, ATV, and DRV. I84A/C are extremely rare non-polymorphic mutations selected primarily by SQV. I84A is associated with markedly reduced susceptibility to each of the PIs. I84C has a less-marked effect on PI susceptibility compared with I84A. $listMutsIn{84(NOT ACV)} is a highly unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR84V">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[I84V is a nonpolymorphic substrate-cleft mutation selected by each of the PIs. I84V reduces susceptibility to LPV, ATV, and DRV.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR85V">
        <!--<DATE>2016-12-09</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[I85V is a non-polymorphic PI-selected mutation. It has minimal, if any, effects on PI susceptibility.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR88ACEFHIKLMPQRVWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[N88S is a non-polymorphic mutation usually selected by NFV, ATV, and IDV. It confers high-level resistance to ATV and increases susceptibility to DRV. N88D is a nonpolymorphic mutation selected by NFV, usually in combination with D30N. It is associated with potential low-level cross-resistance to ATV. $listMutsIn{88(NOT DGST)} is a highly unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR88D">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[N88D is a nonpolymorphic mutation selected by NFV, usually in combination with D30N. It is associated with potential low-level cross-resistance to ATV.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR88S">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[N88S is a non-polymorphic mutation usually selected by NFV, ATV, and IDV. It confers high-level resistance to ATV and increases susceptibility to DRV.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR88TG">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[N88G/T are extremely rare non-polymorphic PI-selected mutations that reduce susceptibility to ATV.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR89VT">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[L89V is a nonpolymorphic accessory mutation weakly selected by each of the PIs. It appears to be minimally associated with reduced PI susceptibility. L89T is an uncommon non-polymorphic PI-selected mutation selected primarily by ATV.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR90ACDEFGHIKNPQRSTVWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[L90M is a non-polymorphic PI-selected mutation that reduces susceptibility to ATV and to a lesser extent LPV. $listMutsIn{90(NOT M)} is a highly unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="PR90M">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>PI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[L90M is a non-polymorphic PI-selected mutation that reduces susceptibility to ATV and to a lesser extent LPV.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RPVIntermediate">
        <!--<DATE>2021-02-22</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[This virus is predicted to have intermediate-level reduced susceptibility to RPV. The use of the combination of CAB/RPV should be considered to be contraindicated.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RPVLow">
        <!--<DATE>2021-02-22</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[This virus is predicted to have low-level reduced susceptibility to RPV. The use of the combination of CAB/RPV should be considered to be relatively contraindicated.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT100ACDEFGHKMNPQRSTWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[L100I is a non-polymorphic mutation that usually occurs in combination with K103N. In this setting it confers high-level resistance to NVP, EFV, and RPV and intermediate resistance to ETR and DOR. L100V is a rare mutations that likely has effects similar to L100I. $listMutsIn{100(NOT IV)} is a highly unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT100I">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[L100I is a non-polymorphic mutation that usually occurs in combination with K103N. In this setting it confers high-level resistance to NVP, EFV, and RPV and intermediate resistance to ETR and DOR.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT100V">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[L100I is a non-polymorphic mutation that usually occurs in combination with K103N. In this setting it confers high-level resistance to NVP, EFV, and RPV and intermediate resistance to ETR and DOR. L100V is a rare mutations that likely has effects similar to L100I.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT101CDFGILMSVWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[K101E is a non-polymorphic accessory mutation that confers intermediate resistance to NVP and RPV and low-level reductions in susceptibility to EFV, ETR, and DOR when it occurs with other NNRTI-resistance mutations. K101H is a non-polymorphic accessory mutation selected by NVP, EFV and ETR. When present with other NNRTI-resistance mutations, it contributes reduces susceptibility to these NNRTIs. K101P is a non-polymorphic mutation that confers high-level resistance to NVP, EFV, RPV, and ETR. Its does not appear to reduce DOR susceptibility. K101Q is a relatively non-polymorphic mutation that is weakly selected in persons receiving NVP and EFV. It is of uncertain phenotypic and clinical significance. $listMutsIn{101(NOT AEHNPQRT)} is a highly unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT101E">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[K101E is a non-polymorphic accessory mutation that confers intermediate resistance to NVP and RPV and low-level reductions in susceptibility to EFV, ETR, and DOR when it occurs with other NNRTI-resistance mutations.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT101H">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[K101H is a non-polymorphic accessory mutation selected by NVP, EFV and ETR. When present with other NNRTI-resistance mutations, it contributes reduces susceptibility to these NNRTIs.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT101NAT">
        <!--<DATE>2016-12-09</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[K101N/A/T are uncommon non-polymorphic NNRTI-selected mutation of uncertain phenotypic and clinical significance.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT101P">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[K101P is a non-polymorphic mutation that confers high-level resistance to NVP, EFV, RPV, and ETR. Its does not appear to reduce DOR susceptibility.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT101Q">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[K101Q is a relatively non-polymorphic mutation that is weakly selected in persons receiving NVP and EFV. It is of uncertain phenotypic and clinical significance.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT103ACDFGILMPVWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[K103N is a non-polymorphic mutation that confers high-level reductions in NVP and EFV susceptibility. K103S is a non-polymorphic mutation that causes high-level reductions in NVP susceptibility but intermediate reductions in EFV susceptibility. Because K103S is a 2-bp change from the wildtype K and a 1-bp change from K103N, persons with K103S may be likely to have once had K103N. It is the most commonly transmitted DRM. K103T is an extremely rare non-polymorphic mutation that appears to confer intermediate/high-level resistance to NVP but it has little if any effect on EFV susceptibility. K103H is a rare non-polymorphic mutation that confers high-level resistance to NVP and EFV. K103E/Q are rare mutations that have not been associated with reduced NNRTI susceptibility. $listMutsIn{103(NOT EHNQRST)} is a highly unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT103EQ">
        <!--<DATE>2016-12-09</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[K103E/Q are rare mutations that have not been associated with reduced NNRTI susceptibility.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT103H">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[K103H is a rare non-polymorphic mutation that confers high-level resistance to NVP and EFV.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT103N">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[K103N is a non-polymorphic mutation that confers high-level reductions in NVP and EFV susceptibility. It is the most commonly transmitted DRM.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT103R">
        <!--<DATE>2018-10-11</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[K103R is a polymorphic mutation that alone has no effect on NNRTI susceptibility. However, in combination with V179D, it reduces NVP and EFV susceptibility about 15-fold.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT103S">
        <!--<DATE>2018-10-11</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[K103S is a non-polymorphic mutation that causes high-level reductions in NVP susceptibility but intermediate reductions in EFV susceptibility. Because K103S is a 2-bp change from the wildtype K and a 1-bp change from K103N, persons with K103S may be likely to have once had K103N.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT103T">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[K103T is an extremely rare non-polymorphic mutation that appears to confer intermediate/high-level resistance to NVP but it has little if any effect on EFV susceptibility.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT106A">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[V106A is a non-polymorphic mutation that confers high-level resistance to NVP and DOR, and intermediate resistance to EFV. It is commonly selected in vitro and in vivo by DOR.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT106CDEFGHKLNPQRSTWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[V106A is a non-polymorphic mutation that confers high-level resistance to NVP and DOR, and intermediate resistance to EFV. V106M is a non-polymorphic mutation that confers high-level resistance to NVP and EFV. It is selected in vitro and in vivo by DOR and preliminary data suggests it reduces DOR susceptibility about 3-fold. It is commonly selected in vitro and in vivo by DOR. $listMutsIn{106(NOT AIM)} is a highly unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT106I">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[V106I occurs in 1% to 2% of viruses from untreated persons. It contributes to reduced NNRTI susceptibility only in combination with other NNRTI-resistance mutations. It is commonly selected in persons receiving DOR in combination with mutations at position 227.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT106M">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[V106M is a non-polymorphic mutation that confers high-level resistance to NVP and EFV. It is selected in vitro and in vivo by DOR and preliminary data suggests it reduces DOR susceptibility about 3-fold.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT108ACDEFGHKLMNPQRSTWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[V108I is a relatively non-polymorphic accessory mutation selected in vitro and/or in vivo with each of the NNRTIs. It appears to contribute to reduced susceptibility to most NNRTIs only in combination with other NNRTI-resistance mutations. $listMutsIn{108(NOT I)} is a highly unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT108I">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[V108I is a relatively non-polymorphic accessory mutation selected in vitro and/or in vivo with each of the NNRTIs. It appears to contribute to reduced susceptibility to most NNRTIs only in combination with other NNRTI-resistance mutations.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT115ACDEGHIKLMNPQRSTVWid">
        <!--<DATE>2016-12-09</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[Y115F causes intermediate resistance to ABC and low-level resistance to TDF. $listMutsIn{115(NOT F)} is a highly unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT115F">
        <!--<DATE>2016-12-09</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[Y115F causes intermediate resistance to ABC and low-level resistance to TDF.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT116ACDEGHIKLMNPQRSTVWid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[F116Y usually occurs in combination with the multi-NRTI resistance mutation Q151M. When it occurs alone, its clinical significance is unknown. $listMutsIn{116(NOT Y)} is a highly unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT116Y">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[F116Y usually occurs in combination with the multi-NRTI resistance mutation Q151M. When it occurs alone, its clinical significance is unknown.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT118I">
        <!--<DATE>2016-12-09</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[V118I is a polymorphic accessory NRTI-resistance mutation that often occurs in combination with multiple TAMs.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT132ML">
        <!--<DATE>2016-12-09</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[I132M is an extremely rare non-polymorphic mutation associated with uncertain amount of reduced NVP and EFV susceptibility. I132L is a more common, non-polymorphic NNRTI-selected mutation that has not been well studied.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT138A">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[E138A is a common polymorphic accessory mutation weakly selected in persons receiving ETR and RPV. It reduces ETR and RPV susceptibility ~2-fold. Its effect on ETR- and RPV-containing regimens is likely to be minimal.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT138CDFHILMNPSTVWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[E138K is a non-polymorphic mutation selected in a high proportion of persons receiving RPV. It reduces RPV susceptibility 2 to 3-fold. In combination with K101E or the NRTI-resistance mutation M184I, it is sufficient to cause VF on a first-line RPV-containing regimen. E138K causes low-level cross-resistance to ETR. E138A is a common polymorphic accessory mutation weakly selected in persons receiving ETR and RPV. It reduces ETR and RPV susceptibility ~2-fold. Its effect on ETR- and RPV-containing regimens is likely to be minimal. E138Q/G are non-polymorphic accessory mutations  selected by ETR occasionally NVP and EFV. They cause low-level reductions in susceptibility to NVP, RPV, and ETR. E138R is an extremely rare non-polymorphic accessory mutation selected in vitro by RPV. Its  effect on NNRTI susceptibility has not been well studied. $listMutsIn{138(NOT AGKQR)} is an unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT138K">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[E138K is a non-polymorphic mutation selected in a high proportion of persons receiving RPV. It reduces RPV susceptibility 2 to 3-fold. In combination with K101E or the NRTI-resistance mutation M184I, it is sufficient to cause VF on a first-line RPV-containing regimen. E138K causes low-level cross-resistance to ETR.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT138QG">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[E138Q/G are non-polymorphic accessory mutations  selected by ETR occasionally NVP and EFV. They cause low-level reductions in susceptibility to NVP, RPV, and ETR.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT138R">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[E138R is an extremely rare non-polymorphic accessory mutation selected in vitro by RPV. Its  effect on NNRTI susceptibility has not been well studied.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT151ACDEFGHIKNPRSTVWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[Q151M causes intermediate/high-level resistance to AZT and ABC, and low-level resistance to TDF, 3TC and FTC. In combination with two or more accessory mutations at positions 62, 75, 77, and 116, it  confers high-level resistance to AZT and ABC and intermediate resistance to TDF, 3TC and FTC. Q151L is an extremely rare transitional mutation that may precede the emergence of the Q151M. $listMutsIn{151(NOT ML)} is a highly unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT151L">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[Q151M causes intermediate/high-level resistance to AZT and ABC, and low-level resistance to TDF, 3TC and FTC. In combination with two or more accessory mutations at positions 62, 75, 77, and 116, it  confers high-level resistance to AZT and ABC and intermediate resistance to TDF, 3TC and FTC. Q151L is an extremely rare transitional mutation that may precede the emergence of the Q151M.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT151M">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[Q151M causes intermediate/high-level resistance to AZT and ABC, and low-level resistance to TDF, 3TC and FTC. In combination with two or more accessory mutations at positions 62, 75, 77, and 116, it  confers high-level resistance to AZT and ABC and intermediate resistance to TDF, 3TC and FTC.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT179ACGHKMNPQRSWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[V179D/E are somewhat polymorphic accessory NNRTI-selected mutation. In combination with other NNRTI DRMs, they appear to contribute low-levels of reduced susceptibility to each of the NNRTIs. In particular, the combinations of K103R/V179D and V106I/V179D act synergistically to reduce NVP and EFV susceptibility. V179F is a non-polymorphic mutation selected in combination with Y181C in persons receiving ETR. Alone it has little effect on NNRTI susceptibility, however in combination with Y181C it is associated with high-level reductions in ETR and RPV susceptibility. V179T is a rare non-polymorphic mutation occasionally selected in persons receiving NNRTIs. It is associated with minimal, if any, reduction in ETR and RPV susceptibility. V179L is a rare non-polymorphic mutation listed as a RPV-associated resistance mutation by the FDA package insert. Its effects on NNRTI susceptibility have not been well studied. $listMutsIn{179(NOT DEFILT)} is an unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT179DE">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[V179D/E are somewhat polymorphic accessory NNRTI-selected mutation. In combination with other NNRTI DRMs, they appear to contribute low-levels of reduced susceptibility to each of the NNRTIs. In particular, the combinations of K103R/V179D and V106I/V179D act synergistically to reduce NVP and EFV susceptibility.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT179F">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[V179F is a non-polymorphic mutation selected in combination with Y181C in persons receiving ETR. Alone it has little effect on NNRTI susceptibility, however in combination with Y181C it is associated with high-level reductions in ETR and RPV susceptibility.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT179I">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[V179I is a polymorphic mutation that is frequently selected in persons receiving ETR and RPV. However, it has little, if any, direct effect on NNRTI susceptibility.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT179L">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[V179L is a rare non-polymorphic mutation listed as a RPV-associated resistance mutation by the FDA package insert. Its effects on NNRTI susceptibility have not been well studied.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT179T">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[V179T is a rare non-polymorphic mutation occasionally selected in persons receiving NNRTIs. It is associated with minimal, if any, reduction in ETR and RPV susceptibility.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT181ADEHKLMNPQRTWid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[Y181C is a non-polymorphic mutation selected in persons receiving NVP, ETR and RPV. It confers high-level resistance to NVP, intermediate resistance to ETR and RPV, and low-level resistance to EFV. It does not significantly reduce DOR susceptibility. Y181I/V are 2-base pair non-polymorphic mutations selected by NVP and ETR. They cause high-level resistance to NVP, ETR, and RPV but not EFV. Their effects on DOR have not been well-characterized. $listMutsIn{181(NOT CIVFSG)} is a highly unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT181C">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[Y181C is a non-polymorphic mutation selected in persons receiving NVP, ETR and RPV. It confers high-level resistance to NVP, intermediate resistance to ETR and RPV, and low-level resistance to EFV. It does not significantly reduce DOR susceptibility.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT181FSG">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[Y181F/S/G are rare non-polymorphic NNRTI-associated mutations that are usually present as part of an electrophoretic mixture. They are likely to represent transitional mutations between Y and I or V.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT181IV">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[Y181I/V are 2-base pair non-polymorphic mutations selected by NVP and ETR. They cause high-level resistance to NVP, ETR, and RPV but not EFV. Their effects on DOR have not been well-characterized.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT184ACDEFGHKLNPQRSTWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[M184V/I cause high-level in vitro resistance to 3TC and FTC and low/intermediate resistance to ABC (3-fold reduced susceptibility). M184V/I are not contraindications to continued treatment with 3TC or FTC because they increase susceptibility to AZT and TDF and are associated with clinically significant reductions in HIV-1 replication. $listMutsIn{184(NOT VI)} is a highly unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT184VI">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[M184V/I cause high-level in vitro resistance to 3TC and FTC and low/intermediate resistance to ABC (3-fold reduced susceptibility). M184V/I are not contraindications to continued treatment with 3TC or FTC because they increase susceptibility to AZT and TDF and are associated with clinically significant reductions in HIV-1 replication.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT188ADEGIKMNPQRSTVWid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[Y188L is a non-polymorphic mutation that confers high-level resistance to NVP, EFV, RPV, and DOR, and potentially low-level resistance to ETR. Y188H is a non-polymorphic mutation selected in persons receiving NVP and EFV. It causes about 5 to 10-fold reduced susceptibility to NVP and EFV. It appears to cause little if any reduction in susceptibility to RPV, ETR, or DOR. Y188C is a non-polymorphic mutation selected in persons receiving NVP and EFV. It confers high-level resistance to NVP and variable levels of reduced susceptibility to EFV. It appears to cause little if any reduction in susceptibility to RPV, ETR, or DOR. $listMutsIn{188(NOT CFHL)} is a highly unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT188C">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[Y188C is a non-polymorphic mutation selected in persons receiving NVP and EFV. It confers high-level resistance to NVP and variable levels of reduced susceptibility to EFV. It appears to cause little if any reduction in susceptibility to RPV, ETR, or DOR.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT188F">
        <!--<DATE>2016-12-09</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[Y188F is a rare non-polymorphic NNRTI-associated mutation that is usually present as part of an electrophoretic mixture. It appears to represent a transitional mutation between Y and L.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT188H">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[Y188H is a non-polymorphic mutation selected in persons receiving NVP and EFV. It causes about 5 to 10-fold reduced susceptibility to NVP and EFV. It appears to cause little if any reduction in susceptibility to RPV, ETR, or DOR.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT188L">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[Y188L is a non-polymorphic mutation that confers high-level resistance to NVP, EFV, RPV, and DOR, and potentially low-level resistance to ETR.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT190A">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[G190A is a non-polymorphic mutation that causes high-level resistance to NVP and intermediate resistance to EFV. It does not significantly reduce susceptibility to RPV, ETR, or DOR.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT190CTV">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[G190C/T/V are rare non-polymorphic mutations that confer high-level resistance to NVP and EFV. Their effects on ETR, RPV, and DOR susceptibility are not known.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT190DFHIKLMNPWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[G190A is a non-polymorphic mutation that causes high-level resistance to NVP and intermediate resistance to EFV. It does not significantly reduce susceptibility to RPV, ETR, or DOR. G190S is a non-polymorphic mutation that confers high-level resistance to NVP and EFV. It may also be associated low-levels reductions in DOR susceptibility. It does not appear to be selected by ETR or RPV or to reduce their in vitro susceptibility. G190E is an uncommon non-polymorphic mutation associated with reduced replication capacity that confers intermediate to high-level resistance to each of the NNRTIs. G190Q is a rare NNRTI-selected mutation that confers high-level NVP and EFV resistance. Its effects on RPV, ETR, and DOR susceptibility is not known. G190C/T/V are rare non-polymorphic mutations that confer high-level resistance to NVP and EFV. Their effects on ETR, RPV, and DOR susceptibility are not known. $listMutsIn{190(NOT ACEQRSTV)} is a highly unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT190EQ">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[G190E is an uncommon non-polymorphic mutation associated with reduced replication capacity that confers intermediate to high-level resistance to each of the NNRTIs. G190Q is a rare NNRTI-selected mutation that confers high-level NVP and EFV resistance. Its effects on RPV, ETR, and DOR susceptibility is not known.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT190S">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[G190S is a non-polymorphic mutation that confers high-level resistance to NVP and EFV. It may also be associated low-levels reductions in DOR susceptibility. It does not appear to be selected by ETR or RPV or to reduce their in vitro susceptibility.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT210W">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[L210W is a TAM that usually occurs in combination with M41L and T215Y. The combination of M41, L210W and T215Y causes high-level resistance to AZT and intermediate resistance to ABC and TDF.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT215GHKMPQRWid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[T215Y/F are TAMs that causes intermediate/high-level resistance to AZT and potentially low-level resistance to ABC and TDF. T215S/C/D/E/I/V/N/A/L do not reduce NRTI susceptibility but arise from viruses that once contained T215Y/F. The presence of one of these revertant mutations suggests that the patient may have once been infected with a virus containing T215Y/F. $listMutsIn{215(NOT YFSCDEIVALN)} is a highly unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT215SCDEIVALN">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[T215Y/F are TAMs that causes intermediate/high-level resistance to AZT and potentially low-level resistance to ABC and TDF. T215S/C/D/E/I/V/N/A/L do not reduce NRTI susceptibility but arise from viruses that once contained T215Y/F. The presence of one of these revertant mutations suggests that the patient may have once been infected with a virus containing T215Y/F.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT215YF">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[T215Y/F are TAMs that causes intermediate/high-level resistance to AZT and potentially low-level resistance to ABC and TDF.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT219ACDFGHILMPSTVYid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[K219E/Q/N/R are accessory TAMS that usually occur in combination with multiple other TAMs. K219W is an uncommon NRTI-selected mutation. $listMutsIn{219(NOT QENRW)} is an unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT219EQNR">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[K219E/Q/N/R are accessory TAMS that usually occur in combination with multiple other TAMs.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT219W">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[K219E/Q/N/R are accessory TAMS that usually occur in combination with multiple other TAMs. K219W is an uncommon NRTI-selected mutation.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT221Y">
        <!--<DATE>2019-09-30</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[H221Y is a non-polymorphic accessory mutation selected primarily by NVP, RPV, and DOR. It frequently occurs in combination with Y181C.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT225ACDEFGIKLMNQRSTVWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2018-10-11</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[P225H is a non-polymorphic EFV-selected mutation that usually occurs in combination with K103N. The combination of P225H and K103N synergistically reduces NVP, EFV and DOR susceptibility. $listMutsIn{225(NOT H)} is a highly unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT225H">
        <!--<DATE>2018-10-11</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[P225H is a non-polymorphic EFV-selected mutation that usually occurs in combination with K103N. The combination of P225H and K103N synergistically reduces NVP, EFV and DOR susceptibility.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT227ADEGHKMNPQRSTWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[F227L is a non-polymorphic mutation that usually occurs in combination with V106A. It is selected in vivo and in vitro with both NVP and DOR. In this context it is associated with high-level reductions in NVP and DOR susceptibility and intermediate reductions in EFV susceptibility. F227I/V are extremely rare mutations that have been selected in vitro by DOR. F227C is a nonpolymorphic mutation selected in persons receiving DOR and rarely in persons receiving ETR and RPV. It usually occurs in combination with other DRMs and in this setting has consistently been associated with the highest possible levels of DOR resistance. It is also usually associated with intermediate or high-level reductions in susceptibility to NVP, EFV, ETR, and RPV. $listMutsIn{227(NOT CILV)} is a highly unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT227C">
        <!--<DATE>2019-09-30</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[F227C is a nonpolymorphic mutation selected in persons receiving DOR and rarely in persons receiving ETR and RPV. It usually occurs in combination with other DRMs and in this setting has consistently been associated with the highest possible levels of DOR resistance. It is also usually associated with intermediate or high-level reductions in susceptibility to NVP, EFV, ETR, and RPV.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT227ILV">
        <!--<DATE>2018-10-11</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[F227L is a non-polymorphic mutation that usually occurs in combination with V106A. It is selected in vivo and in vitro with both NVP and DOR. In this context it is associated with high-level reductions in NVP and DOR susceptibility and intermediate reductions in EFV susceptibility. F227I/V are extremely rare mutations that have been selected in vitro by DOR.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT230ACDEFGHKNPQRSTVWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[M230L is an uncommon non-polymorphic mutation selected in persons receiving EFV, NVP, and RPV. It causes intermediate to high-level resistance to each of the NNRTIs. M230I is a rare mutation selected by RPV. Its effects on NNRTI susceptibility have not been well studied. It also often occurs as a result of APOBEC-mediated G-to-A hypermutation resulting in viruses that are likely to be noninfectious. $listMutsIn{230(NOT IL)} is a highly unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT230I">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[M230I is a rare mutation selected by RPV. Its effects on NNRTI susceptibility have not been well studied. It also often occurs as a result of APOBEC-mediated G-to-A hypermutation resulting in viruses that are likely to be noninfectious.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT230L">
        <!--<DATE>2018-10-11</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[M230L is an uncommon non-polymorphic mutation selected in persons receiving EFV, NVP, and RPV. It causes intermediate to high-level resistance to each of the NNRTIs.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT234ACDEFGHKMNPQRSTWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[L234I is a nonpolymorphic mutation selected in persons receiving NVP and EFV. It is also selected in vitro by ETR and DOR. In combination with V106A, it is associated with high-level DOR resistance. Its effect on susceptibility when it occurs alone has not been well characterized. $listMutsIn{234(NOT I)} is a highly unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT234I">
        <!--<DATE>2019-09-30</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[L234I is a nonpolymorphic mutation selected in persons receiving NVP and EFV. It is also selected in vitro by ETR and DOR. In combination with V106A, it is associated with high-level DOR resistance. Its effect on susceptibility when it occurs alone has not been well characterized.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT236ACDEFGHIKMNQRSTVWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[P236L is a rare mutation selected commonly by DLV, which appears to have little if any effect on current NNRTIs. $listMutsIn{236(NOT L)} is a highly unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT236L">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[P236L is a rare mutation selected commonly by DLV, which appears to have little if any effect on current NNRTIs.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT238ACDEFGHILMPQSVWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[K238T/N are uncommon non-polymorphic mutations selected in persons receiving NVP and EFV usually in combination with K103N. Alone, K238T/N appear to have minimal effects on NNRTI susceptibility. $listMutsIn{238(NOT NRT)} is a highly unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT238TN">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[K238T/N are uncommon non-polymorphic mutations selected in persons receiving NVP and EFV usually in combination with K103N. Alone, K238T/N appear to have minimal effects on NNRTI susceptibility.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT318ACDEGHIKLMNPQRSTVWid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[Y318F is a nonpolymorphic mutation that occurred in 2 of 10 persons with VF and HIVDR while receiving DOR. It confers about 11-fold reduced susceptibility to DOR but otherwise has minimal if any effect on NVP, EFV, and ETR. $listMutsIn{318(NOT F)} is a highly unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT318F">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[Y318F is a nonpolymorphic mutation that occurred in 2 of 10 persons with VF and HIVDR while receiving DOR. It confers about 11-fold reduced susceptibility to DOR but otherwise has minimal if any effect on NVP, EFV, and ETR.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT348ACDEFGHKLMPQRSTVWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[N348I is a non-polymorphic accessory mutation selected by NVP and EFV and the NRTIs AZT and D4T. Alone it reduces AZT and NVP susceptibility by about 3-fold and EFV susceptibility by 2-fold. $listMutsIn{348(NOT I)} is an unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT348I">
        <!--<DATE>2018-10-11</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[N348I is a non-polymorphic accessory mutation selected by NVP and EFV and the NRTIs AZT and D4T. Alone it reduces AZT and NVP susceptibility by about 3-fold and EFV susceptibility by 2-fold.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT40F">
        <!--<DATE>2016-12-09</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[E40F is a non-polymorphic accessory mutation selected by AZT and d4T. It usually occurs in combination with M41L, L210W and T215Y. In this context it is associated with reduced susceptibility to each of the NRTIs.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT41L">
        <!--<DATE>2016-12-09</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[M41L is a TAM that usually occurs with T215Y. In combination, M41L plus T215Y confer intermediate / high-level resistance to AZT and d4T and contribute to reduced ddI, ABC and TDF susceptibility.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT44AD">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[E44D is a relatively non-polymorphic accessory mutation; E44A is a nonpolymorphic accessory mutation. Each usually occurs with multiple TAMs.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT62V">
        <!--<DATE>2016-12-09</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[A62V is an accessory mutation that often occurs in combination with the multi-NRTI resistance mutations K65R or Q151M. A62V is widespread in subtype A viruses in former Soviet Union countries but A62 is otherwise non-polymorphic.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT65ACDFGHILMPQSTVWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-11-20</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[K65R confers intermediate reductions in susceptibility to TDF, ABC, and 3TC/FTC. It increases AZT susceptibility. K65N appears to have reduced replication compared with K65R. K65E is an extremely rare NRTI-selected mutation with markedly reduced replication fitness. Its effect on NRTI susceptibility is uncertain. $listMutsIn{65(NOT NRE)} is a highly unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT65E">
        <!--<DATE>2022-11-20</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[K65R confers intermediate reductions in susceptibility to TDF, ABC, and 3TC/FTC. It increases AZT susceptibility. K65E is an extremely rare NRTI-selected mutation with markedly reduced replication fitness. Its effect on NRTI susceptibility is uncertain.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT65N">
        <!--<DATE>2022-11-20</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[K65R confers intermediate reductions in susceptibility to TDF, ABC, and 3TC/FTC. It increases AZT susceptibility. K65N appears to have reduced replication compared with K65R.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT65R">
        <!--<DATE>2022-11-20</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[K65R confers intermediate reductions in susceptibility to TDF, ABC, and 3TC/FTC. It increases AZT susceptibility. In NRTI-experienced, INSTI-naive patients with K65R, TDF+3TC+DTG is usually highly effective and more effective than AZT/3TC/DTG. However, in patients receiving TDF+3TC+DTG, there is a risk of emergent DTG resistance that does not arise in NRTI-naive patients receiving TDF+3TC+DTG.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT67-70d">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[Amino acid deletions between codons 67 and 70 are rare and usually occur in combination with multiple TAMs, K65R, or the Q151M mutation complex. Deletions at position 67 are more often associated with multiple TAMs. Deletions at positions 69 and 70 are more often associated with K65R or the Q151M mutation complex. Deletions at codon 68 are extremely rare and less well characterized.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT67ACFIKLMPQRVWYi">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[D67N is a non-polymorphic TAM associated with low-level resistance to AZT. D67G/E/S/T/H are non-polymorphic NRTI-selected mutations that generally occur in viruses with multiple TAMs. $listMutsIn{67(NOT NGESTHd)} is a highly unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT67GESTH">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[D67N is a non-polymorphic TAM associated with low-level resistance to AZT. D67G/E/S/T/H are non-polymorphic NRTI-selected mutations that generally occur in viruses with multiple TAMs.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT67N">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[D67N is a non-polymorphic TAM associated with low-level resistance to AZT.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT68G">
        <!--<DATE>2017-02-27</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[S68G is a polymorphic mutation that is often selected in combination with K65R. It partially restores the replication defect associated with K65R.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT69CFHKLMPQRVWY">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[T69D is a nonpolymorphic mutation selected by early NRTIs that does not appear to reduce AZT, ABC, or TDF susceptibility. T69G is a rare non-polymorphic mutation that usually occurs in viruses with a deletion at codon 67 and multiple other NRTI-resistance mutations. T69N/S/A/I/E are relatively non-polymorphic mutations weakly selected in persons receiving NRTIs. They may minimally contribute reduced AZT susceptibility. $listMutsIn{69(NOT DNGSAIEid)} is a highly unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT69D">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[T69D is a nonpolymorphic mutation selected by early NRTIs that does not appear to reduce AZT, ABC, or TDF susceptibility.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT69G">
        <!--<DATE>2016-12-09</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[T69G is a rare non-polymorphic mutation that usually occurs in viruses with a deletion at codon 67 and multiple other NRTI-resistance mutations.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT69i">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[Amino acid insertions between codons 67 and 70 are by convention assigned to codon 69. Together with TAMs, they are associated with high-level resistance to AZT, ABC and TDF, and intermediate to 3TC and FTC.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT69NSAIE">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[T69N/S/A/I/E are relatively non-polymorphic mutations weakly selected in persons receiving NRTIs. They may minimally contribute reduced AZT susceptibility.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT70ACDFHILMPVWYi">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[K70R is a TAM that confers intermediate resistance to AZT and contributes to reduced ABC and TDF susceptibility in combination with other TAMs. K70/E/Q/N/T/S/G cause low-leve resistance to ABC and TDF. $listMutsIn{70(NOT REGQNSTd)} is an unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT70EGQNST">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[K70/E/Q/N/T/S/G cause low-leve resistance to ABC and TDF.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT70R">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[K70R is a TAM that confers intermediate resistance to AZT and contributes to reduced ABC and TDF susceptibility in combination with other TAMs.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT74ACDEFGHKMNPQRSTWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[L74V causes intermediate ABC resistance. L74I causes low-level ABC resistance. $listMutsIn{74(NOT VI)} is a highly unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT74VI">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[L74V causes intermediate ABC resistance. L74I causes low-level ABC resistance.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT75CDEFGHKNPQRWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2022-11-20</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[V75I is a relatively non-polymorphic accessory mutation that often occurs in combination with the multi-NRTI resistance mutation Q151M. When it occurs alone, its clinical significance is uncertain. V75T/M/A/S are nonpolymorphic accessory NRTI-selected mutations. They appear to have minimal phenotypic effects on AZT, ABC, and TDF. $listMutsIn{75(NOT MTISAL)} is a highly unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT75I">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[V75I is a relatively non-polymorphic accessory mutation that often occurs in combination with the multi-NRTI resistance mutation Q151M. When it occurs alone, its clinical significance is uncertain.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT75MTAS">
        <!--<DATE>2022-11-20</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[V75T/M/A/S are nonpolymorphic accessory NRTI-selected mutations. They appear to have minimal phenotypic effects on AZT, ABC, and TDF.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT77ACDEGHIKMNPQRSTVWYid">
        <!--<DATE>2016-12-09</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[F77L usually occurs in combination with the multi-NRTI resistance mutation Q151M. When it occurs alone, its clinical significance is uncertain. $listMutsIn{77(NOT L)} is a highly unusual mutation at this position.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT77L">
        <!--<DATE>2016-12-09</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[F77L usually occurs in combination with the multi-NRTI resistance mutation Q151M. When it occurs alone, its clinical significance is uncertain.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT90I">
        <!--<DATE>2022-10-24</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[V90I is a polymorphic accessory mutation weakly selected by each of the NNRTIs. It is associated with minimal, if any, detectable reduction in NNRTI susceptibility.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
      <COMMENT_STRING id="RT98G">
        <!--<DATE>2016-12-09</DATE>-->
        <!--<DRUGCLASS>NNRTI</DRUGCLASS>-->
        <TEXT><![CDATA[A98G is a non-polymorphic accessory mutation associated with low-level reduced susceptibility to each of the NNRTIs.]]></TEXT>
        <SORT_TAG>1</SORT_TAG>
      </COMMENT_STRING>
    </COMMENT_DEFINITIONS>
  </DEFINITIONS>
  <DRUG>
    <NAME>ABC</NAME>
    <FULLNAME>abacavir</FULLNAME>
    <RULE>
      <CONDITION><![CDATA[SCORE FROM (
  41L => 5,
  62V => 5,
  MAX(65E => 10, 65N => 30, 65R => 45),
  MAX(67E => 5, 67G => 5, 67H => 5, 67N => 5, 67S => 5, 67T => 5, 67d => 30),
  68d => 15,
  MAX(69G => 10, 69i => 60, 69d => 15),
  MAX(70E => 15, 70G => 15, 70N => 15, 70Q => 15, 70R => 5, 70S => 15, 70T => 15, 70d => 15),
  MAX(74I => 15, 74V => 30),
  75I => 5,
  77L => 5,
  115F => 30,
  116Y => 5,
  MAX(151L => 30, 151M => 60),
  MAX(184I => 15, 184V => 15),
  210W => 5,
  MAX(215F => 10, 215I => 5, 215V => 5, 215Y => 10),
  MAX(219E => 5, 219N => 5, 219Q => 5, 219R => 5, 219W => 5),
  151M AND 184IV => 10,
  65RN AND 151M => 10,
  77L AND 116Y AND 151ML => 15,
  74V AND 184IV => 15,
  115F AND 184IV => 15,
  41L AND 215FY => 10,
  210W AND 215FY => 10,
  41L AND 210W => 10,
  41L AND 210W AND 215FY => 10,
  41L AND 44AD AND 210W AND 215FY => 5,
  40F AND 41L AND 210W AND 215FY => 5,
  41L AND 67EGNHST AND 215FY => 5,
  67EGNHST AND 215FY AND 219ENQRW => 5,
  67EGNHST AND 70R AND 219ENQRW => 10,
  41L AND 184VI AND 215FY => 10,
  67EGNHST AND 70R AND 184VI AND 219ENQRW => 10
)]]></CONDITION>
      <ACTIONS>
        <SCORERANGE>
          <USE_GLOBALRANGE/>
        </SCORERANGE>
      </ACTIONS>
    </RULE>
  </DRUG>
  <DRUG>
    <NAME>AZT</NAME>
    <FULLNAME>zidovudine</FULLNAME>
    <RULE>
      <CONDITION><![CDATA[SCORE FROM (
  41L => 15,
  62V => 5,
  65R => -10,
  MAX(67E => 15, 67G => 15, 67H => 15, 67N => 15, 67S => 15, 67T => 15, 67d => 30),
  MAX(69G => 5, 69i => 60),
  70R => 30,
  MAX(75I => 5, 75M => 10, 75A => 10, 75S => 10, 75T => 10),
  77L => 10,
  116Y => 10,
  MAX(151L => 30, 151M => 60),
  MAX(184I => -10, 184V => -10),
  210W => 15,
  MAX(215A => 10, 215C => 10, 215D => 10, 215E => 10, 215F => 60, 215I => 20, 215L => 10, 215N => 10, 215S => 10, 215V => 20, 215Y => 60),
  MAX(219E => 10, 219N => 10, 219Q => 10, 219R => 10, 219W => 10),
  151M AND 184IV => 10,
  65RN AND 151M => 10,
  77L AND 116Y AND 151ML => 10,
  MAX(41L AND 215FY => 10, 41L AND 215ACDEILNSV => 10),
  MAX(210W AND 215FY => 10, 210W AND 215ACDEILNSV => 10),
  41L AND 210W => 10,
  41L AND 44AD AND 210W AND 215FY => 5,
  40F AND 41L AND 210W AND 215FY => 5,
  41L AND 67EGNHST AND 215FY => 5,
  67EGNHST AND 215FY AND 219ENQRW => 5,
  67EGNHST AND 70R AND 219ENQRW => 15
)]]></CONDITION>
      <ACTIONS>
        <SCORERANGE>
          <USE_GLOBALRANGE/>
        </SCORERANGE>
      </ACTIONS>
    </RULE>
  </DRUG>
  <DRUG>
    <NAME>D4T</NAME>
    <FULLNAME>stavudine</FULLNAME>
    <RULE>
      <CONDITION><![CDATA[SCORE FROM (
  41L => 15,
  62V => 5,
  MAX(65E => 10, 65N => 30, 65R => 60),
  MAX(67E => 10, 67G => 10, 67H => 10, 67N => 15, 67S => 10, 67T => 10, 67d => 30),
  68d => 30,
  MAX(69G => 10, 69i => 60, 69d => 30, 69D => 10),
  MAX(70E => 15, 70G => 15, 70N => 15, 70Q => 15, 70R => 15, 70S => 15, 70T => 15, 70d => 30),
  MAX(75I => 5, 75M => 30, 75A => 30, 75S => 30, 75T => 60),
  77L => 10,
  116Y => 10,
  MAX(151L => 30, 151M => 60),
  MAX(184I => -10, 184V => -10),
  210W => 15,
  MAX(215A => 20, 215C => 20, 215D => 20, 215E => 20, 215F => 40, 215I => 20, 215L => 20, 215N => 20, 215S => 20, 215V => 20, 215Y => 40),
  MAX(219E => 10, 219N => 10, 219Q => 10, 219R => 10, 219W => 10),
  40F AND 41L AND 210W AND 215FY => 5,
  41L AND 210W => 10,
  41L AND 44AD AND 210W AND 215FY => 5,
  41L AND 67EGN AND 215FY => 5,
  67EGN AND 215FY AND 219ENQR => 5,
  67EGN AND 70R AND 219ENQR => 10,
  70R AND 215FY => 5,
  77L AND 116Y AND 151M => 10,
  MAX(210W AND 215ACDEILNSV => 5, 210W AND 215FY => 10),
  MAX(41L AND 215ACDEILNSV => 5, 41L AND 215FY => 10),
  151M AND 184IV => 10,
  70EGNQST AND 184IV => 10
)]]></CONDITION>
      <ACTIONS>
        <SCORERANGE>
          <USE_GLOBALRANGE/>
        </SCORERANGE>
      </ACTIONS>
    </RULE>
  </DRUG>
  <DRUG>
    <NAME>DDI</NAME>
    <FULLNAME>didanosine</FULLNAME>
    <RULE>
      <CONDITION><![CDATA[SCORE FROM (
  41L => 10,
  62V => 5,
  MAX(65E => 10, 65N => 30, 65R => 60),
  MAX(67E => 5, 67G => 5, 67H => 5, 67N => 5, 67S => 5, 67T => 5, 67d => 30),
  68d => 30,
  MAX(69G => 10, 69i => 60, 69d => 30, 69D => 30),
  MAX(70E => 15, 70G => 15, 70N => 15, 70Q => 15, 70R => 10, 70S => 15, 70T => 15, 70d => 30),
  MAX(74I => 60, 74V => 60),
  MAX(75I => 5, 75M => 15, 75A => 15, 75S => 15, 75T => 30),
  77L => 10,
  116Y => 10,
  MAX(151L => 30, 151M => 60),
  MAX(184I => 10, 184V => 10),
  210W => 10,
  MAX(215A => 10, 215C => 10, 215D => 10, 215E => 10, 215F => 15, 215I => 10, 215L => 10, 215N => 10, 215S => 10, 215V => 10, 215Y => 15),
  MAX(219E => 5, 219N => 5, 219Q => 5, 219R => 5, 219W => 5),
  40F AND 41L AND 210W AND 215FY => 5,
  41L AND 210W => 10,
  41L AND 44AD AND 210W AND 215FY => 5,
  41L AND 67EGN AND 215FY => 5,
  67EGN AND 215FY AND 219ENQR => 5,
  67EGN AND 70R AND 219ENQR => 10,
  70R AND 215FY => 5,
  77L AND 116Y AND 151M => 10,
  MAX(210W AND 215ACDEILNSV => 5, 210W AND 215FY => 10),
  MAX(41L AND 215ACDEILNSV => 5, 41L AND 215FY => 10)
)]]></CONDITION>
      <ACTIONS>
        <SCORERANGE>
          <USE_GLOBALRANGE/>
        </SCORERANGE>
      </ACTIONS>
    </RULE>
  </DRUG>
  <DRUG>
    <NAME>FTC</NAME>
    <FULLNAME>emtricitabine</FULLNAME>
    <RULE>
      <CONDITION><![CDATA[SCORE FROM (
  MAX(65N => 15, 65R => 30),
  67d => 15,
  68d => 15,
  MAX(69i => 30, 69d => 15),
  MAX(70E => 10, 70G => 10, 70N => 10, 70Q => 10, 70S => 10, 70T => 10, 70d => 10),
  75I => 5,
  77L => 5,
  116Y => 5,
  MAX(151L => 10, 151M => 15),
  MAX(184I => 60, 184V => 60),
  65RN AND 151M => 10,
  77L AND 116Y AND 151ML => 15,
  41L AND 215FY => 5,
  41L AND 210W AND 215FY => 15,
  67EGNHST AND 70R AND 219ENQRW => 10
)]]></CONDITION>
      <ACTIONS>
        <SCORERANGE>
          <USE_GLOBALRANGE/>
        </SCORERANGE>
      </ACTIONS>
    </RULE>
  </DRUG>
  <DRUG>
    <NAME>3TC</NAME>
    <FULLNAME>lamivudine</FULLNAME>
    <RULE>
      <CONDITION><![CDATA[SCORE FROM (
  MAX(65N => 15, 65R => 30),
  67d => 15,
  68d => 15,
  MAX(69i => 30, 69d => 15),
  MAX(70E => 10, 70G => 10, 70N => 10, 70Q => 10, 70S => 10, 70T => 10, 70d => 10),
  75I => 5,
  77L => 5,
  116Y => 5,
  MAX(151L => 10, 151M => 15),
  MAX(184I => 60, 184V => 60),
  65RN AND 151M => 10,
  77L AND 116Y AND 151ML => 15,
  41L AND 215FY => 5,
  41L AND 210W AND 215FY => 15,
  67EGNHST AND 70R AND 219ENQRW => 10
)]]></CONDITION>
      <ACTIONS>
        <SCORERANGE>
          <USE_GLOBALRANGE/>
        </SCORERANGE>
      </ACTIONS>
    </RULE>
  </DRUG>
  <DRUG>
    <NAME>TDF</NAME>
    <FULLNAME>tenofovir</FULLNAME>
    <RULE>
      <CONDITION><![CDATA[SCORE FROM (
  41L => 5,
  62V => 5,
  MAX(65E => 10, 65N => 45, 65R => 50),
  MAX(67E => 5, 67G => 5, 67H => 5, 67N => 5, 67S => 5, 67T => 5, 67d => 30),
  68d => 15,
  MAX(69G => 5, 69i => 60, 69d => 15),
  MAX(70E => 15, 70G => 15, 70N => 15, 70Q => 15, 70R => 5, 70S => 15, 70T => 15, 70d => 15),
  74I => 5,
  75I => 5,
  77L => 5,
  115F => 15,
  116Y => 5,
  MAX(151L => 10, 151M => 15),
  MAX(184I => -10, 184V => -10),
  210W => 5,
  MAX(215F => 10, 215I => 5, 215V => 5, 215Y => 10),
  MAX(219E => 5, 219N => 5, 219Q => 5, 219R => 5, 219W => 5),
  151M AND 184IV => 15,
  65RN AND 151M => 10,
  77L AND 116Y AND 151ML => 15,
  115F AND 184IV => 5,
  70EGNQST AND 184IV => 10,
  65R AND 68NGR => 5,
  62V AND 65R => 5,
  41L AND 215FY => 10,
  210W AND 215FY => 10,
  41L AND 210W => 10,
  41L AND 210W AND 215FY => 10,
  41L AND 44AD AND 210W AND 215FY => 5,
  40F AND 41L AND 210W AND 215FY => 5,
  41L AND 67EGNHST AND 215FY => 5,
  67EGNHST AND 215FY AND 219ENQRW => 5,
  67EGNHST AND 70R AND 219ENQRW => 10
)]]></CONDITION>
      <ACTIONS>
        <SCORERANGE>
          <USE_GLOBALRANGE/>
        </SCORERANGE>
      </ACTIONS>
    </RULE>
  </DRUG>
  <DRUG>
    <NAME>DOR</NAME>
    <FULLNAME>doravirine</FULLNAME>
    <RULE>
      <CONDITION><![CDATA[SCORE FROM(98G => 15,
                         MAX ( 100I => 15, 100V => 10 ),
                         MAX ( 101E => 15, 101P => 10 ),
                         MAX ( 106A => 60, 106I => 10, 106M => 30 ),
                         108I => 10,
                         138K => 5,
                         179F => 10,
                         MAX ( 181C => 10, 181I => 20, 181V => 20 ),
                         MAX ( 188C => 5, 188F => 30, 188H => 5, 188L => 60 ),
                         MAX ( 190C => 10, 190E => 60, 190Q => 30, 190S => 20, 190T => 10, 190V => 10 ),
                         221Y => 10,
                         225H => 20,
                         MAX ( 227C => 60, 227I => 60, 227L => 60, 227V => 60 ),
                         MAX ( 230I => 15, 230L => 60 ),
                         234I => 45,
                         236L => 10,
                         318F => 60,
                         (100I AND 103N) => 15,
                         (100I AND 103N AND 225H) => -10,
                         (103N AND 181C) => 5,
                         (103N AND 225H) => 10,
                         (106I AND 181C) => 5,
                         (106I AND 190S) => 5,
                         (108I AND 181C) => 5,
                         (108I AND 234I) => 10,
                         (181CIV AND 190ACSTV) => 10,
                         (181CIV AND 221Y) => 10,
                         (98G AND 181C) => 5,
                         (98G AND 227CL) => 15,
                         MAX ((101E AND 190A) => 5, (101E AND 190S) => 5))]]></CONDITION>
      <ACTIONS>
        <SCORERANGE>
          <USE_GLOBALRANGE/>
        </SCORERANGE>
      </ACTIONS>
    </RULE>
  </DRUG>
  <DRUG>
    <NAME>EFV</NAME>
    <FULLNAME>efavirenz</FULLNAME>
    <RULE>
      <CONDITION><![CDATA[SCORE FROM(98G => 15,
                         MAX ( 100I => 60, 100V => 30 ),
                         MAX ( 101E => 15, 101H => 10, 101P => 60 ),
                         MAX ( 103H => 60, 103N => 60, 103S => 45, 103T => 15 ),
                         MAX ( 106A => 45, 106M => 60 ),
                         108I => 10,
                         MAX ( 138G => 10, 138K => 10, 138Q => 10, 138R => 10 ),
                         MAX ( 179D => 10, 179E => 10, 179F => 10, 179L => 10 ),
                         MAX ( 181C => 30, 181F => 15, 181G => 15, 181I => 30, 181S => 15, 181V => 30 ),
                         MAX ( 188C => 60, 188F => 60, 188H => 30, 188L => 60 ),
                         MAX ( 190A => 45, 190C => 60, 190E => 60, 190Q => 60, 190S => 60, 190T => 60, 190V => 60 ),
                         221Y => 10,
                         225H => 45,
                         MAX ( 227C => 45, 227I => 10, 227L => 15, 227V => 10 ),
                         MAX ( 230I => 15, 230L => 45 ),
                         MAX ( 238N => 10, 238T => 30 ),
                         318F => 10,
                         (101E AND 181C) => 5,
                         (103R AND 179D) => 20,
                         (106A AND 227CL) => 15,
                         (98G AND 181C) => 5,
                         (98G AND 227CL) => 15)]]></CONDITION>
      <ACTIONS>
        <SCORERANGE>
          <USE_GLOBALRANGE/>
        </SCORERANGE>
      </ACTIONS>
    </RULE>
  </DRUG>
  <DRUG>
    <NAME>ETR</NAME>
    <FULLNAME>etravirine</FULLNAME>
    <RULE>
      <CONDITION><![CDATA[SCORE FROM(98G => 10,
                         MAX ( 100I => 30, 100V => 10 ),
                         MAX ( 101E => 15, 101H => 10, 101P => 60 ),
                         106I => 10,
                         MAX ( 138A => 10, 138G => 10, 138K => 10, 138Q => 10, 138R => 10 ),
                         MAX ( 179D => 10, 179E => 10, 179F => 15, 179L => 10 ),
                         MAX ( 181C => 30, 181F => 15, 181G => 15, 181I => 60, 181S => 15, 181V => 60 ),
                         188L => 10,
                         MAX ( 190A => 10, 190C => 10, 190E => 45, 190Q => 45, 190S => 10, 190T => 10, 190V => 10 ),
                         221Y => 10,
                         227C => 30,
                         MAX ( 230I => 15, 230L => 30 ),
                         (101E AND 181C) => 5,
                         (101E AND 188L) => 5,
                         (181CIV AND 190ACSTV) => 10,
                         (98G AND 181C) => 5,
                         (98G AND 227CL) => 15,
                         MAX ((101E AND 190A) => 5, (101E AND 190S) => 5),
                         MAX ((179F AND 181C) => 15, (179T AND 181C) => 10))]]></CONDITION>
      <ACTIONS>
        <SCORERANGE>
          <USE_GLOBALRANGE/>
        </SCORERANGE>
      </ACTIONS>
    </RULE>
  </DRUG>
  <DRUG>
    <NAME>NVP</NAME>
    <FULLNAME>nevirapine</FULLNAME>
    <RULE>
      <CONDITION><![CDATA[SCORE FROM(98G => 30,
                         MAX ( 100I => 60, 100V => 30 ),
                         MAX ( 101E => 30, 101H => 15, 101P => 60 ),
                         MAX ( 103H => 60, 103N => 60, 103S => 60, 103T => 60 ),
                         MAX ( 106A => 60, 106I => 10, 106M => 60 ),
                         108I => 15,
                         MAX ( 138G => 10, 138K => 10, 138Q => 10, 138R => 10 ),
                         MAX ( 179D => 10, 179E => 10, 179F => 15, 179L => 10 ),
                         MAX ( 181C => 60, 181F => 60, 181G => 60, 181I => 60, 181S => 60, 181V => 60 ),
                         MAX ( 188C => 60, 188F => 60, 188H => 60, 188L => 60 ),
                         MAX ( 190A => 60, 190C => 60, 190E => 60, 190Q => 60, 190S => 60, 190T => 60, 190V => 60 ),
                         221Y => 15,
                         225H => 45,
                         MAX ( 227C => 45, 227I => 30, 227L => 30, 227V => 30 ),
                         MAX ( 230I => 30, 230L => 60 ),
                         MAX ( 238N => 10, 238T => 30 ),
                         318F => 30,
                         348I => 15,
                         (101E AND 181C) => 5,
                         (103R AND 179D) => 20,
                         (98G AND 181C) => 5,
                         (98G AND 227CL) => 15)]]></CONDITION>
      <ACTIONS>
        <SCORERANGE>
          <USE_GLOBALRANGE/>
        </SCORERANGE>
      </ACTIONS>
    </RULE>
  </DRUG>
  <DRUG>
    <NAME>RPV</NAME>
    <FULLNAME>rilpivirine</FULLNAME>
    <RULE>
      <CONDITION><![CDATA[SCORE FROM(98G => 15,
                         MAX ( 100I => 60, 100V => 15 ),
                         MAX ( 101E => 45, 101H => 10, 101P => 60 ),
                         106I => 10,
                         MAX ( 138A => 15, 138G => 15, 138K => 45, 138Q => 15, 138R => 15 ),
                         MAX ( 179D => 10, 179E => 10, 179F => 15, 179L => 15 ),
                         MAX ( 181C => 45, 181F => 30, 181G => 30, 181I => 60, 181S => 30, 181V => 60 ),
                         MAX ( 188F => 30, 188L => 60 ),
                         MAX ( 190A => 15, 190C => 10, 190E => 60, 190Q => 45, 190S => 15, 190T => 10, 190V => 10 ),
                         221Y => 15,
                         227C => 45,
                         MAX ( 230I => 30, 230L => 60 ),
                         (101E AND 184I) => 15,
                         (103R AND 179D) => 15,
                         (106I AND 181C) => 10,
                         (138K AND 184I) => 15,
                         (181CIV AND 190ACSTV) => 10,
                         (181CIV AND 221Y) => 10,
                         (98G AND 181C) => 5,
                         (98G AND 227CL) => 15,
                         MAX ((179F AND 181C) => 15, (179T AND 181C) => 10))]]></CONDITION>
      <ACTIONS>
        <SCORERANGE>
          <USE_GLOBALRANGE/>
        </SCORERANGE>
      </ACTIONS>
    </RULE>
  </DRUG>
  <DRUG>
    <NAME>ATV/r</NAME>
    <FULLNAME>atazanavir/r</FULLNAME>
    <RULE>
      <CONDITION><![CDATA[SCORE FROM(20T => 5,
                         MAX ( 24F => 5, 24I => 10, 24M => 5 ),
                         32I => 15,
                         33F => 5,
                         MAX ( 46I => 10, 46L => 10, 46V => 10 ),
                         47V => 10,
                         MAX ( 48A => 10, 48L => 10, 48M => 30, 48Q => 10, 48S => 10, 48T => 10, 48V => 30 ),
                         50L => 60,
                         53L => 10,
                         MAX ( 54A => 15, 54L => 15, 54M => 15, 54S => 15, 54T => 15, 54V => 15 ),
                         MAX ( 73A => 10, 73C => 10, 73D => 5, 73S => 10, 73T => 10, 73V => 5 ),
                         74P => 10,
                         MAX ( 82A => 15, 82C => 15, 82F => 15, 82L => 10, 82M => 10, 82S => 30, 82T => 30 ),
                         83D => 10,
                         MAX ( 84A => 60, 84C => 60, 84V => 60 ),
                         MAX ( 88D => 10, 88G => 15, 88S => 60, 88T => 15 ),
                         90M => 25,
                         (32I AND 47AV) => 5,
                         (32I AND 54LM) => 5,
                         (46IL AND 84V AND 90M) => 5,
                         (46ILV AND 82ACFLMST) => 10,
                         (46ILV AND 90M) => 10,
                         (47AV AND 54LM) => 5,
                         (53L AND 90M) => 10,
                         (54ALMSTV AND 82ACFLMST) => 10,
                         (54ALMSTV AND 90M) => 10,
                         (73ACSTV AND 90M) => 10,
                         (82ACFLMST AND 90M) => 10)]]></CONDITION>
      <ACTIONS>
        <SCORERANGE>
          <USE_GLOBALRANGE/>
        </SCORERANGE>
      </ACTIONS>
    </RULE>
  </DRUG>
  <DRUG>
    <NAME>DRV/r</NAME>
    <FULLNAME>darunavir/r</FULLNAME>
    <RULE>
      <CONDITION><![CDATA[SCORE FROM(10F => 5,
                         32I => 15,
                         33F => 5,
                         MAX ( 47A => 10, 47V => 10 ),
                         MAX ( 50L => -10, 50V => 20 ),
                         MAX ( 54L => 20, 54M => 20 ),
                         74P => 5,
                         76V => 20,
                         82F => 15,
                         MAX ( 84A => 30, 84C => 15, 84V => 15 ),
                         88S => -5,
                         89V => 5,
                         (11IL AND 32I) => 5,
                         (11IL AND 54LM) => 5,
                         (32I AND 47AV) => 5,
                         (32I AND 54LM) => 5,
                         (32I AND 76V) => 5,
                         (32I AND 84V) => 5,
                         (32I AND 89V) => 5,
                         (47AV AND 54LM) => 5,
                         (47AV AND 84V) => 5,
                         (54LM AND 84V) => 5,
                         (54LM AND 89V) => 5)]]></CONDITION>
      <ACTIONS>
        <SCORERANGE>
          <USE_GLOBALRANGE/>
        </SCORERANGE>
      </ACTIONS>
    </RULE>
  </DRUG>
  <DRUG>
    <NAME>FPV/r</NAME>
    <FULLNAME>fosamprenavir/r</FULLNAME>
    <RULE>
      <CONDITION><![CDATA[SCORE FROM(10F => 15,
                         20T => 5,
                         MAX ( 24F => 5, 24I => 10, 24M => 5 ),
                         32I => 30,
                         33F => 10,
                         MAX ( 46I => 10, 46L => 10, 46V => 10 ),
                         MAX ( 47A => 60, 47V => 35 ),
                         MAX ( 50L => -5, 50V => 60 ),
                         MAX ( 54A => 10, 54L => 60, 54M => 60, 54S => 10, 54T => 10, 54V => 10 ),
                         MAX ( 73A => 10, 73C => 10, 73D => 5, 73S => 10, 73T => 10, 73V => 5 ),
                         74P => 10,
                         76V => 60,
                         MAX ( 82A => 15, 82C => 15, 82F => 30, 82L => 15, 82M => 15, 82S => 15, 82T => 15 ),
                         MAX ( 84A => 60, 84C => 60, 84V => 60 ),
                         88S => -10,
                         89V => 10,
                         90M => 20,
                         (11IL AND 32I) => 5,
                         (11IL AND 54LM) => 5,
                         (32I AND 47AV) => 5,
                         (32I AND 54LM) => 5,
                         (32I AND 76V) => 5,
                         (32I AND 84V) => 5,
                         (32I AND 89V) => 5,
                         (46IL AND 84V AND 90M) => 5,
                         (46ILV AND 76V) => 10,
                         (46ILV AND 82ACFLMST) => 10,
                         (46ILV AND 90M) => 10,
                         (47AV AND 54LM) => 5,
                         (47AV AND 84V) => 5,
                         (53L AND 90M) => 10,
                         (54ALMSTV AND 82ACFLMST) => 10,
                         (54ALMSTV AND 90M) => 10,
                         (54LM AND 84V) => 5,
                         (54LM AND 89V) => 5,
                         (73ACSTV AND 90M) => 10,
                         (82ACFLMST AND 90M) => 10)]]></CONDITION>
      <ACTIONS>
        <SCORERANGE>
          <USE_GLOBALRANGE/>
        </SCORERANGE>
      </ACTIONS>
    </RULE>
  </DRUG>
  <DRUG>
    <NAME>IDV/r</NAME>
    <FULLNAME>indinavir/r</FULLNAME>
    <RULE>
      <CONDITION><![CDATA[SCORE FROM(10F => 10,
                         20T => 5,
                         MAX ( 24F => 5, 24I => 15, 24M => 5 ),
                         32I => 15,
                         33F => 5,
                         MAX ( 46I => 10, 46L => 10, 46V => 10 ),
                         MAX ( 47A => 15, 47V => 15 ),
                         MAX ( 48A => 10, 48L => 10, 48M => 10, 48Q => 10, 48S => 10, 48T => 10, 48V => 10 ),
                         50L => -5,
                         MAX ( 54A => 15, 54L => 10, 54M => 15, 54S => 15, 54T => 15, 54V => 15 ),
                         MAX ( 73A => 15, 73C => 15, 73D => 5, 73S => 15, 73T => 15, 73V => 5 ),
                         74P => 10,
                         76V => 30,
                         MAX ( 82A => 30, 82C => 15, 82F => 30, 82L => 10, 82M => 30, 82S => 30, 82T => 30 ),
                         83D => 10,
                         MAX ( 84A => 60, 84C => 60, 84V => 60 ),
                         88S => 15,
                         89V => 5,
                         90M => 30,
                         (11IL AND 32I) => 5,
                         (11IL AND 54LM) => 5,
                         (32I AND 47AV) => 5,
                         (32I AND 54LM) => 5,
                         (32I AND 76V) => 5,
                         (32I AND 84V) => 5,
                         (32I AND 89V) => 5,
                         (46IL AND 84V AND 90M) => 5,
                         (46ILV AND 76V) => 10,
                         (46ILV AND 82ACFLMST) => 10,
                         (46ILV AND 90M) => 10,
                         (47AV AND 54LM) => 5,
                         (47AV AND 84V) => 5,
                         (53L AND 90M) => 10,
                         (54ALMSTV AND 82ACFLMST) => 10,
                         (54ALMSTV AND 90M) => 10,
                         (54LM AND 84V) => 5,
                         (54LM AND 89V) => 5,
                         (73ACSTV AND 90M) => 10,
                         (82ACFLMST AND 90M) => 10)]]></CONDITION>
      <ACTIONS>
        <SCORERANGE>
          <USE_GLOBALRANGE/>
        </SCORERANGE>
      </ACTIONS>
    </RULE>
  </DRUG>
  <DRUG>
    <NAME>LPV/r</NAME>
    <FULLNAME>lopinavir/r</FULLNAME>
    <RULE>
      <CONDITION><![CDATA[SCORE FROM(10F => 5,
                         MAX ( 24F => 5, 24I => 10, 24M => 5 ),
                         32I => 15,
                         33F => 5,
                         MAX ( 46I => 10, 46L => 10, 46V => 5 ),
                         MAX ( 47A => 60, 47V => 15 ),
                         MAX ( 48A => 10, 48L => 10, 48M => 10, 48Q => 10, 48S => 10, 48T => 10, 48V => 10 ),
                         MAX ( 50L => -10, 50V => 30 ),
                         MAX ( 54A => 15, 54L => 20, 54M => 20, 54S => 15, 54T => 15, 54V => 15 ),
                         MAX ( 73A => 5, 73C => 5, 73D => 5, 73S => 5, 73T => 5, 73V => 5 ),
                         74P => 5,
                         76V => 30,
                         MAX ( 82A => 30, 82C => 15, 82F => 30, 82L => 10, 82M => 25, 82S => 30, 82T => 30 ),
                         MAX ( 84A => 60, 84C => 30, 84V => 30 ),
                         90M => 15,
                         (11IL AND 32I) => 5,
                         (11IL AND 54LM) => 5,
                         (32I AND 47AV) => 5,
                         (32I AND 54LM) => 5,
                         (32I AND 76V) => 5,
                         (32I AND 84V) => 5,
                         (32I AND 89V) => 5,
                         (46IL AND 84V AND 90M) => 5,
                         (46ILV AND 76V) => 10,
                         (46ILV AND 82ACFLMST) => 10,
                         (47AV AND 54LM) => 5,
                         (47AV AND 84V) => 5,
                         (54ALMSTV AND 82ACFLMST) => 10,
                         (54ALMSTV AND 90M) => 5,
                         (54LM AND 84V) => 5,
                         (54LM AND 89V) => 5,
                         (82ACFLMST AND 90M) => 5)]]></CONDITION>
      <ACTIONS>
        <SCORERANGE>
          <USE_GLOBALRANGE/>
        </SCORERANGE>
      </ACTIONS>
    </RULE>
  </DRUG>
  <DRUG>
    <NAME>NFV</NAME>
    <FULLNAME>nelfinavir</FULLNAME>
    <RULE>
      <CONDITION><![CDATA[SCORE FROM(10F => 15,
                         20T => 15,
                         23I => 15,
                         MAX ( 24F => 10, 24I => 10, 24M => 10 ),
                         30N => 60,
                         32I => 15,
                         33F => 10,
                         43T => 10,
                         MAX ( 46I => 30, 46L => 20, 46V => 20 ),
                         MAX ( 47A => 30, 47V => 20 ),
                         MAX ( 48A => 30, 48L => 30, 48M => 30, 48Q => 30, 48S => 30, 48T => 30, 48V => 30 ),
                         50V => 15,
                         53L => 10,
                         MAX ( 54A => 20, 54L => 20, 54M => 20, 54S => 20, 54T => 20, 54V => 20 ),
                         58E => 10,
                         MAX ( 73A => 15, 73C => 15, 73D => 10, 73S => 15, 73T => 15, 73V => 10 ),
                         74P => 20,
                         76V => 10,
                         MAX ( 82A => 30, 82C => 30, 82F => 30, 82L => 10, 82M => 30, 82S => 30, 82T => 30 ),
                         83D => 15,
                         MAX ( 84A => 60, 84C => 60, 84V => 60 ),
                         MAX ( 88D => 60, 88G => 30, 88S => 60, 88T => 30 ),
                         89V => 10,
                         90M => 60,
                         (11IL AND 32I) => 5,
                         (11IL AND 54LM) => 5,
                         (32I AND 47AV) => 5,
                         (32I AND 54LM) => 5,
                         (32I AND 76V) => 5,
                         (32I AND 84V) => 5,
                         (32I AND 89V) => 5,
                         (46IL AND 84V AND 90M) => 5,
                         (46ILV AND 76V) => 10,
                         (46ILV AND 82ACFLMST) => 10,
                         (46ILV AND 90M) => 10,
                         (47AV AND 54LM) => 5,
                         (47AV AND 84V) => 5,
                         (53L AND 90M) => 10,
                         (54ALMSTV AND 82ACFLMST) => 10,
                         (54ALMSTV AND 90M) => 10,
                         (54LM AND 84V) => 5,
                         (54LM AND 89V) => 5,
                         (73ACSTV AND 90M) => 10,
                         (82ACFLMST AND 90M) => 10)]]></CONDITION>
      <ACTIONS>
        <SCORERANGE>
          <USE_GLOBALRANGE/>
        </SCORERANGE>
      </ACTIONS>
    </RULE>
  </DRUG>
  <DRUG>
    <NAME>SQV/r</NAME>
    <FULLNAME>saquinavir/r</FULLNAME>
    <RULE>
      <CONDITION><![CDATA[SCORE FROM(20T => 5,
                         MAX ( 24F => 5, 24I => 10, 24M => 5 ),
                         33F => 5,
                         MAX ( 46I => 10, 46L => 10, 46V => 5 ),
                         MAX ( 48A => 60, 48L => 60, 48M => 60, 48Q => 60, 48S => 60, 48T => 60, 48V => 60 ),
                         MAX ( 50L => -5, 50V => 15 ),
                         53L => 15,
                         MAX ( 54A => 15, 54L => 15, 54M => 15, 54S => 15, 54T => 15, 54V => 15 ),
                         MAX ( 73A => 15, 73C => 15, 73D => 10, 73S => 15, 73T => 15, 73V => 10 ),
                         74P => 10,
                         MAX ( 82A => 15, 82C => 15, 82F => 10, 82L => 10, 82M => 15, 82S => 15, 82T => 15 ),
                         83D => 10,
                         MAX ( 84A => 60, 84C => 60, 84V => 60 ),
                         MAX ( 88D => 10, 88S => 15 ),
                         90M => 45,
                         (46IL AND 84V AND 90M) => 5,
                         (46ILV AND 82ACFLMST) => 10,
                         (46ILV AND 90M) => 5,
                         (53L AND 90M) => 10,
                         (54ALMSTV AND 82ACFLMST) => 10,
                         (54ALMSTV AND 90M) => 10,
                         (73ACSTV AND 90M) => 10,
                         (82ACFLMST AND 90M) => 10)]]></CONDITION>
      <ACTIONS>
        <SCORERANGE>
          <USE_GLOBALRANGE/>
        </SCORERANGE>
      </ACTIONS>
    </RULE>
  </DRUG>
  <DRUG>
    <NAME>TPV/r</NAME>
    <FULLNAME>tipranavir/r</FULLNAME>
    <RULE>
      <CONDITION><![CDATA[SCORE FROM(24I => -5,
                         32I => 5,
                         33F => 10,
                         43T => 10,
                         MAX ( 46I => 5, 46L => 10, 46V => 5 ),
                         MAX ( 47A => 30, 47V => 30 ),
                         MAX ( 50L => -5, 50V => -5 ),
                         MAX ( 54A => 20, 54L => -10, 54M => 20, 54S => 20, 54T => 20, 54V => 20 ),
                         58E => 15,
                         74P => 25,
                         76V => -5,
                         MAX ( 82C => 10, 82L => 45, 82M => 10, 82S => 30, 82T => 45 ),
                         83D => 25,
                         MAX ( 84A => 60, 84C => 30, 84V => 30 ),
                         (46IL AND 84V AND 90M) => 5)]]></CONDITION>
      <ACTIONS>
        <SCORERANGE>
          <USE_GLOBALRANGE/>
        </SCORERANGE>
      </ACTIONS>
    </RULE>
  </DRUG>
  <DRUG>
    <NAME>BIC</NAME>
    <FULLNAME>bictegravir</FULLNAME>
    <RULE>
      <CONDITION><![CDATA[SCORE FROM(51Y => 10,
                         MAX ( 66I => 5, 66K => 15 ),
                         92Q => 10,
                         118R => 30,
                         MAX ( 121C => 15, 121Y => 10 ),
                         MAX ( 138A => 10, 138K => 10, 138T => 10 ),
                         MAX ( 140A => 10, 140C => 10, 140R => 10, 140S => 10 ),
                         MAX ( 143A => 5, 143C => 5, 143G => 5, 143H => 5, 143K => 5, 143R => 5, 143S => 5 ),
                         147G => 10,
                         MAX ( 148H => 25, 148K => 30, 148R => 25 ),
                         151L => 15,
                         MAX ( 153F => 15, 153Y => 15 ),
                         155H => 10,
                         230R => 10,
                         263K => 30,
                         (118R AND 138AKT) => 10,
                         (138AKT AND 140ACS) => 10,
                         (138AKT AND 148HKR) => 10,
                         (140ACS AND 148HKR) => 10,
                         (140ACS AND 148HKR AND 149A) => 10,
                         (143ACGHRS AND 163R) => 5,
                         (143ACGHRS AND 230R) => 5,
                         (147G AND 148HKR) => 15,
                         (147G AND 155H) => 10,
                         (148HKR AND 155H) => 20,
                         (148HKR AND 163KR) => 5,
                         (155H AND 263K) => 20,
                         (157Q AND 263K) => 10,
                         (51Y AND 263K) => 10,
                         (74FIM AND 118R) => 10,
                         (74FIM AND 143ACGHRS) => 5,
                         (74FIM AND 148HKR) => 15,
                         (92Q AND 155H) => 10,
                         (97A AND 118R) => 10,
                         (97A AND 148HKR) => 15)]]></CONDITION>
      <ACTIONS>
        <SCORERANGE>
          <USE_GLOBALRANGE/>
        </SCORERANGE>
      </ACTIONS>
    </RULE>
  </DRUG>
  <DRUG>
    <NAME>CAB</NAME>
    <FULLNAME>cabotegravir</FULLNAME>
    <RULE>
      <CONDITION><![CDATA[SCORE FROM(51Y => 15,
                         MAX ( 66I => 10, 66K => 20 ),
                         MAX ( 92G => 10, 92Q => 15, 92V => 10 ),
                         118R => 60,
                         MAX ( 121C => 60, 121Y => 15 ),
                         MAX ( 138A => 10, 138K => 10, 138T => 10 ),
                         MAX ( 140A => 10, 140C => 10, 140R => 60, 140S => 10 ),
                         MAX ( 143A => 10, 143C => 10, 143G => 10, 143H => 10, 143K => 10, 143R => 10, 143S => 10 ),
                         146P => 30,
                         147G => 10,
                         MAX ( 148H => 30, 148K => 50, 148N => 15, 148R => 40 ),
                         151L => 15,
                         MAX ( 153F => 25, 153Y => 25 ),
                         MAX ( 155H => 25, 155S => 15, 155T => 15 ),
                         230R => 20,
                         263K => 30,
                         (118R AND 138AKT) => 10,
                         (138AKT AND 140ACS) => 15,
                         (138AKT AND 148HKR) => 20,
                         (140ACS AND 148HKR) => 20,
                         (140ACS AND 148HKR AND 149A) => 10,
                         (143ACGHRS AND 163R) => 5,
                         (143ACGHRS AND 230R) => 5,
                         (147G AND 148HKR) => 20,
                         (147G AND 155H) => 25,
                         (148HKR AND 155H) => 20,
                         (148HKR AND 163KR) => 20,
                         (155H AND 263K) => 20,
                         (157Q AND 263K) => 10,
                         (51Y AND 263K) => 10,
                         (74FIM AND 118R) => 10,
                         (74FIM AND 143ACGHRS) => 10,
                         (74FIM AND 148HKR) => 15,
                         (92Q AND 155H) => 20,
                         (97A AND 118R) => 10,
                         (97A AND 143ACGHRS) => 5,
                         (97A AND 148HKR) => 20)]]></CONDITION>
      <ACTIONS>
        <SCORERANGE>
          <USE_GLOBALRANGE/>
        </SCORERANGE>
      </ACTIONS>
    </RULE>
  </DRUG>
  <DRUG>
    <NAME>DTG</NAME>
    <FULLNAME>dolutegravir</FULLNAME>
    <RULE>
      <CONDITION><![CDATA[SCORE FROM(51Y => 10,
                         MAX ( 66I => 5, 66K => 15 ),
                         92Q => 10,
                         118R => 50,
                         MAX ( 121C => 15, 121Y => 10 ),
                         MAX ( 138A => 10, 138K => 10, 138T => 10 ),
                         MAX ( 140A => 10, 140C => 10, 140R => 10, 140S => 10 ),
                         MAX ( 143A => 5, 143C => 5, 143G => 5, 143H => 5, 143K => 5, 143R => 5, 143S => 5 ),
                         147G => 10,
                         MAX ( 148H => 25, 148K => 30, 148R => 25 ),
                         151L => 15,
                         MAX ( 153F => 15, 153Y => 15 ),
                         155H => 10,
                         230R => 20,
                         263K => 30,
                         (118R AND 138AKT) => 10,
                         (138AKT AND 140ACS) => 10,
                         (138AKT AND 148HKR) => 10,
                         (140ACS AND 148HKR) => 10,
                         (140ACS AND 148HKR AND 149A) => 10,
                         (143ACGHRS AND 163R) => 5,
                         (143ACGHRS AND 230R) => 5,
                         (147G AND 148HKR) => 15,
                         (147G AND 155H) => 10,
                         (148HKR AND 155H) => 20,
                         (148HKR AND 163KR) => 5,
                         (155H AND 263K) => 20,
                         (157Q AND 263K) => 10,
                         (51Y AND 263K) => 10,
                         (74FIM AND 118R) => 10,
                         (74FIM AND 143ACGHRS) => 5,
                         (74FIM AND 148HKR) => 15,
                         (92Q AND 155H) => 10,
                         (97A AND 118R) => 10,
                         (97A AND 148HKR) => 15)]]></CONDITION>
      <ACTIONS>
        <SCORERANGE>
          <USE_GLOBALRANGE/>
        </SCORERANGE>
      </ACTIONS>
    </RULE>
  </DRUG>
  <DRUG>
    <NAME>EVG</NAME>
    <FULLNAME>elvitegravir</FULLNAME>
    <RULE>
      <CONDITION><![CDATA[SCORE FROM(51Y => 15,
                         MAX ( 66A => 60, 66I => 60, 66K => 60 ),
                         MAX ( 92G => 30, 92Q => 60, 92V => 60 ),
                         95K => 10,
                         97A => 10,
                         118R => 60,
                         MAX ( 121C => 60, 121Y => 60 ),
                         MAX ( 138A => 15, 138K => 15, 138T => 15 ),
                         MAX ( 140A => 30, 140C => 30, 140R => 30, 140S => 30 ),
                         MAX ( 143A => 10, 143C => 10, 143G => 10, 143H => 10, 143K => 10, 143R => 10, 143S => 10 ),
                         145S => 60,
                         146P => 60,
                         147G => 60,
                         MAX ( 148H => 60, 148K => 60, 148N => 15, 148R => 60 ),
                         MAX ( 151A => 30, 151L => 60 ),
                         MAX ( 153F => 25, 153Y => 25 ),
                         MAX ( 155H => 60, 155S => 30, 155T => 30 ),
                         157Q => 10,
                         MAX ( 163K => 15, 163R => 15 ),
                         230R => 20,
                         232N => 10,
                         263K => 30,
                         (118R AND 138AKT) => 10,
                         (138AKT AND 140ACS) => 15,
                         (140ACS AND 148HKR AND 149A) => 10,
                         (143ACGHRS AND 163R) => 5,
                         (143ACGHRS AND 230R) => 5,
                         (147G AND 155H) => 10,
                         (51Y AND 263K) => 15,
                         (74FIM AND 118R) => 10,
                         (74FIM AND 143ACGHRS) => 5,
                         (74FIM AND 148HKR) => 15,
                         (92Q AND 155H) => 10,
                         (97A AND 118R) => 10,
                         (97A AND 143ACGHRS) => 5)]]></CONDITION>
      <ACTIONS>
        <SCORERANGE>
          <USE_GLOBALRANGE/>
        </SCORERANGE>
      </ACTIONS>
    </RULE>
  </DRUG>
  <DRUG>
    <NAME>RAL</NAME>
    <FULLNAME>raltegravir</FULLNAME>
    <RULE>
      <CONDITION><![CDATA[SCORE FROM(51Y => 15,
                         MAX ( 66A => 15, 66I => 15, 66K => 60 ),
                         MAX ( 92G => 15, 92Q => 30, 92V => 30 ),
                         95K => 10,
                         97A => 10,
                         118R => 60,
                         MAX ( 121C => 60, 121Y => 60 ),
                         MAX ( 138A => 15, 138K => 15, 138T => 15 ),
                         MAX ( 140A => 30, 140C => 30, 140R => 30, 140S => 30 ),
                         MAX ( 143A => 60, 143C => 60, 143G => 60, 143H => 60, 143K => 60, 143R => 60, 143S => 60 ),
                         147G => 10,
                         MAX ( 148H => 60, 148K => 60, 148N => 15, 148R => 60 ),
                         MAX ( 151A => 15, 151L => 30 ),
                         MAX ( 153F => 10, 153Y => 10 ),
                         MAX ( 155H => 60, 155S => 30, 155T => 30 ),
                         157Q => 10,
                         MAX ( 163K => 15, 163R => 15 ),
                         230R => 20,
                         232N => 10,
                         263K => 25,
                         (118R AND 138AKT) => 10,
                         (138AKT AND 140ACS) => 15,
                         (140ACS AND 148HKR AND 149A) => 10,
                         (74FIM AND 118R) => 10,
                         (74FIM AND 148HKR) => 15,
                         (92Q AND 155H) => 10,
                         (97A AND 118R) => 10)]]></CONDITION>
      <ACTIONS>
        <SCORERANGE>
          <USE_GLOBALRANGE/>
        </SCORERANGE>
      </ACTIONS>
    </RULE>
  </DRUG>
  <DRUG>
    <NAME>LEN</NAME>
    <FULLNAME>lenacapavir</FULLNAME>
    <RULE>
      <CONDITION>SCORE FROM (9999A =&gt; 0)</CONDITION>
      <ACTIONS>
        <SCORERANGE>
          <USE_GLOBALRANGE/>
        </SCORERANGE>
      </ACTIONS>
    </RULE>
  </DRUG>
  <MUTATION_COMMENTS>
    <GENE>
      <NAME>CA</NAME>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>105TSE</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="CA105TSE"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>107NS</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="CA107NS"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>56I</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="CA56I"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>57S</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="CA57S"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>66I</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="CA66I"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>67H</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="CA67H"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>70NHRS</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="CA70NHRS"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>74DS</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="CA74DS"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
    </GENE>
    <GENE>
      <NAME>IN</NAME>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>118ACDEFHIKLMNPQSTVWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN118ACDEFHIKLMNPQSTVWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>118R</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN118R"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>119R</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN119R"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>121ADEGHIKLMNPQRSTVWid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN121ADEGHIKLMNPQRSTVWid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>121C</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN121C"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>121Y</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN121Y"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>128T</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN128T"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>138CFGHILMNPQRSVWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN138CFGHILMNPQRSVWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>138D</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN138D"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>138KAT</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN138KAT"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>140DEFHIKLMNPQTVWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN140DEFHIKLMNPQTVWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>140R</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN140R"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>140SAC</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN140SAC"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>143CRH</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN143CRH"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>143DEFILMNPQTVWid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN143DEFILMNPQTVWid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>143KGSA</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN143KGSA"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>145ACDEFGHIKLMNQRTVWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN145ACDEFGHIKLMNQRTVWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>145S</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN145S"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>146ACDEFGHIKLMNRSTVWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN146ACDEFGHIKLMNRSTVWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>146PRL</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN146PRL"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>147ACDEFHIKLMNPQRTVWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN147ACDEFHIKLMNPQRTVWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>147G</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN147G"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>148ACDEFGILMPSTVWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN148ACDEFGILMPSTVWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>148HKR</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN148HKR"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>148N</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN148N"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>149A</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN149A"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>151A</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN151A"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>151CDEFGHKMNPQRSTWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN151CDEFGHKMNPQRSTWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>151I</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN151I"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>151L</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN151L"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>153ACDEGHIKLMNPQRTVWid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN153ACDEGHIKLMNPQRTVWid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>153YFA</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN153YFA"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>155ACDEFGIKLMPQRVWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN155ACDEFGIKLMPQRVWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>155H</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN155H"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>155ST</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN155ST"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>157Q</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN157Q"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>163RK</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN163RK"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>230N</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN230N"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>230R</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN230R"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>232N</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN232N"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>263ACDEFGHILMNPQSTVWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN263ACDEFGHILMNPQSTVWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>263K</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN263K"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>49G</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN49G"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>50I</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN50I"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>51ACDEFGIKLMNPQRSTVWid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN51ACDEFGIKLMNPQRSTVWid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>51Y</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN51Y"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>66AI</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN66AI"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>66CDEFGHLMNPQRSVWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN66CDEFGHLMNPQRSVWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>66K</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN66K"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>74F</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN74F"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>74I</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN74I"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>74M</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN74M"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>92ACDFHIKLMNPRSTWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN92ACDFHIKLMNPRSTWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>92GV</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN92GV"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>92Q</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN92Q"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>95K</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN95K"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>97A</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="IN97A"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
    </GENE>
    <GENE>
      <NAME>PR</NAME>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>10ACDEGHKMNPQSTWid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR10ACDEGHKMNPQSTWid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>10F</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR10F"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>10IV</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR10IV"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>10RY</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR10RY"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>11IL</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR11IL"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>20I</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR20I"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>20MV</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR20MV"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>20R</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR20R"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>20T</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR20T"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>23I</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR23I"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>24ACDEGHKNPQRSTVWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR24ACDEGHKNPQRSTVWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>24FM</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR24FM"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>24I</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR24I"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>30ACEFGHIKLMPQRSTVWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR30ACEFGHIKLMPQRSTVWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>30N</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR30N"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>32ACDEFGHKLMNPQRSTWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR32ACDEFGHKLMNPQRSTWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>32I</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR32I"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>33i OR 34i OR 35i OR 36i OR 37i OR 38i OR 39i OR 40i OR 41i</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR33-41i"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>33F</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR33F"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>33IV</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR33IV"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>43T</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR43T"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>46ACDEFGHKNPQRSTWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR46ACDEFGHKNPQRSTWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>46IL</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR46IL"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>46V</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR46V"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>47A</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR47A"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>47CDEFGHKLMNPQRSTWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR47CDEFGHKLMNPQRSTWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>47V</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR47V"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>48ASTQL</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR48ASTQL"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>48CDEFHIKNPRWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR48CDEFHIKNPRWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>48M</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR48M"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>48V</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR48V"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>50ACDEFGHKMNPQRSTWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR50ACDEFGHKMNPQRSTWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>50L</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR50L"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>50V</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR50V"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>53LY</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR53LY"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>54ATS</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR54ATS"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>54CDEFGHKNPQRWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR54CDEFGHKNPQRWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>54LM</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR54LM"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>54V</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR54V"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>58E</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR58E"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>71IL</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR71IL"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>71TV</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR71TV"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>73EFHIKLMNPQRWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR73EFHIKLMNPQRWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>73STCA</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR73STCA"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>74P</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR74P"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>74S</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR74S"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>76ACDEFGHIKMNPQRSTWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR76ACDEFGHIKMNPQRSTWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>76V</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR76V"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>82A</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR82A"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>82C</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR82C"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>82DEGHKNPQRWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR82DEGHKNPQRWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>82F</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR82F"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>82I</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR82I"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>82L</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR82L"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>82M</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR82M"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>82TS</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR82TS"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>83D</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR83D"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>84AC</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR84AC"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>84DEFGHKLMNPQRSTWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR84DEFGHKLMNPQRSTWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>84V</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR84V"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>85V</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR85V"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>88ACEFHIKLMPQRVWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR88ACEFHIKLMPQRVWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>88D</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR88D"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>88S</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR88S"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>88TG</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR88TG"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>89VT</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR89VT"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>90ACDEFGHIKNPQRSTVWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR90ACDEFGHIKNPQRSTVWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>90M</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="PR90M"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
    </GENE>
    <GENE>
      <NAME>RT</NAME>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>100ACDEFGHKMNPQRSTWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT100ACDEFGHKMNPQRSTWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>100I</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT100I"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>100V</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT100V"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>101CDFGILMSVWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT101CDFGILMSVWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>101E</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT101E"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>101H</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT101H"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>101NAT</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT101NAT"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>101P</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT101P"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>101Q</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT101Q"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>103ACDFGILMPVWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT103ACDFGILMPVWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>103EQ</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT103EQ"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>103H</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT103H"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>103N</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT103N"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>103R</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT103R"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>103S</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT103S"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>103T</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT103T"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>106A</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT106A"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>106CDEFGHKLNPQRSTWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT106CDEFGHKLNPQRSTWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>106I</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT106I"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>106M</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT106M"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>108ACDEFGHKLMNPQRSTWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT108ACDEFGHKLMNPQRSTWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>108I</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT108I"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>115ACDEGHIKLMNPQRSTVWid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT115ACDEGHIKLMNPQRSTVWid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>115F</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT115F"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>116ACDEGHIKLMNPQRSTVWid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT116ACDEGHIKLMNPQRSTVWid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>116Y</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT116Y"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>118I</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT118I"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>132ML</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT132ML"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>138A</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT138A"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>138CDFHILMNPSTVWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT138CDFHILMNPSTVWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>138K</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT138K"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>138QG</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT138QG"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>138R</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT138R"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>151ACDEFGHIKNPRSTVWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT151ACDEFGHIKNPRSTVWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>151L</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT151L"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>151M</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT151M"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>179ACGHKMNPQRSWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT179ACGHKMNPQRSWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>179DE</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT179DE"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>179F</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT179F"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>179I</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT179I"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>179L</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT179L"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>179T</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT179T"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>181ADEHKLMNPQRTWid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT181ADEHKLMNPQRTWid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>181C</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT181C"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>181FSG</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT181FSG"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>181IV</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT181IV"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>184ACDEFGHKLNPQRSTWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT184ACDEFGHKLNPQRSTWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>184VI</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT184VI"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>188ADEGIKMNPQRSTVWid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT188ADEGIKMNPQRSTVWid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>188C</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT188C"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>188F</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT188F"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>188H</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT188H"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>188L</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT188L"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>190A</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT190A"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>190CTV</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT190CTV"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>190DFHIKLMNPWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT190DFHIKLMNPWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>190EQ</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT190EQ"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>190S</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT190S"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>210W</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT210W"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>215GHKMPQRWid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT215GHKMPQRWid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>215SCDEIVALN</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT215SCDEIVALN"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>215YF</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT215YF"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>219ACDFGHILMPSTVYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT219ACDFGHILMPSTVYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>219EQNR</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT219EQNR"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>219W</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT219W"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>221Y</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT221Y"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>225ACDEFGIKLMNQRSTVWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT225ACDEFGIKLMNQRSTVWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>225H</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT225H"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>227ADEGHKMNPQRSTWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT227ADEGHKMNPQRSTWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>227C</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT227C"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>227ILV</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT227ILV"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>230ACDEFGHKNPQRSTVWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT230ACDEFGHKNPQRSTVWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>230I</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT230I"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>230L</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT230L"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>234ACDEFGHKMNPQRSTWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT234ACDEFGHKMNPQRSTWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>234I</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT234I"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>236ACDEFGHIKMNQRSTVWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT236ACDEFGHIKMNQRSTVWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>236L</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT236L"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>238ACDEFGHILMPQSVWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT238ACDEFGHILMPQSVWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>238TN</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT238TN"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>318ACDEGHIKLMNPQRSTVWid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT318ACDEGHIKLMNPQRSTVWid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>318F</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT318F"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>348ACDEFGHKLMPQRSTVWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT348ACDEFGHKLMPQRSTVWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>348I</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT348I"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>40F</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT40F"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>41L</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT41L"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>44AD</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT44AD"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>62V</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT62V"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>65ACDFGHILMPQSTVWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT65ACDFGHILMPQSTVWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>65E</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT65E"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>65N</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT65N"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>65R</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT65R"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>67d OR 68d OR 69d OR 70d</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT67-70d"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>67ACFIKLMPQRVWYi</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT67ACFIKLMPQRVWYi"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>67GESTH</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT67GESTH"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>67N</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT67N"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>68G</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT68G"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>69CFHKLMPQRVWY</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT69CFHKLMPQRVWY"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>69D</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT69D"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>69G</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT69G"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>69i</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT69i"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>69NSAIE</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT69NSAIE"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>70ACDFHILMPVWYi</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT70ACDFHILMPVWYi"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>70EGQNST</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT70EGQNST"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>70R</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT70R"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>74ACDEFGHKMNPQRSTWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT74ACDEFGHKMNPQRSTWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>74VI</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT74VI"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>75CDEFGHKNPQRWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT75CDEFGHKNPQRWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>75I</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT75I"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>75MTAS</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT75MTAS"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>77ACDEGHIKMNPQRSTVWYid</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT77ACDEGHIKMNPQRSTVWYid"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>77L</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT77L"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>90I</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT90I"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
      <RULE>
        <CONDITION>98G</CONDITION>
        <ACTIONS>
          <COMMENT ref="RT98G"/>
        </ACTIONS>
      </RULE>
    </GENE>
  </MUTATION_COMMENTS>
  <RESULT_COMMENTS>
    <RESULT_COMMENT_RULE>
      <DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITIONS>
        <DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITION>
          <DRUG_NAME>CAB</DRUG_NAME>
          <EQ>4</EQ>
        </DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITION>
      </DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITIONS>
      <LEVEL_ACTION>
        <COMMENT ref="CABIntermediate"/>
      </LEVEL_ACTION>
    </RESULT_COMMENT_RULE>
    <RESULT_COMMENT_RULE>
      <DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITIONS>
        <DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITION>
          <DRUG_NAME>CAB</DRUG_NAME>
          <EQ>3</EQ>
        </DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITION>
      </DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITIONS>
      <LEVEL_ACTION>
        <COMMENT ref="CABLow"/>
      </LEVEL_ACTION>
    </RESULT_COMMENT_RULE>
    <RESULT_COMMENT_RULE>
      <DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITIONS>
        <DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITION>
          <DRUG_NAME>DTG</DRUG_NAME>
          <EQ>5</EQ>
        </DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITION>
      </DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITIONS>
      <LEVEL_ACTION>
        <COMMENT ref="DTGHigh"/>
      </LEVEL_ACTION>
    </RESULT_COMMENT_RULE>
    <RESULT_COMMENT_RULE>
      <DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITIONS>
        <DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITION>
          <DRUG_NAME>DTG</DRUG_NAME>
          <EQ>4</EQ>
        </DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITION>
      </DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITIONS>
      <LEVEL_ACTION>
        <COMMENT ref="DTGIntermediate"/>
      </LEVEL_ACTION>
    </RESULT_COMMENT_RULE>
    <RESULT_COMMENT_RULE>
      <DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITIONS>
        <DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITION>
          <DRUG_NAME>DTG</DRUG_NAME>
          <EQ>3</EQ>
        </DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITION>
      </DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITIONS>
      <LEVEL_ACTION>
        <COMMENT ref="DTGLow"/>
      </LEVEL_ACTION>
    </RESULT_COMMENT_RULE>
    <RESULT_COMMENT_RULE>
      <DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITIONS>
        <DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITION>
          <DRUG_NAME>DRV/r</DRUG_NAME>
          <EQ>5</EQ>
        </DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITION>
      </DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITIONS>
      <LEVEL_ACTION>
        <COMMENT ref="DRVHigh"/>
      </LEVEL_ACTION>
    </RESULT_COMMENT_RULE>
    <RESULT_COMMENT_RULE>
      <DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITIONS>
        <DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITION>
          <DRUG_NAME>DRV/r</DRUG_NAME>
          <EQ>5</EQ>
        </DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITION>
        <DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITION>
          <DRUG_NAME>TPV/r</DRUG_NAME>
          <EQ>4</EQ>
        </DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITION>
      </DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITIONS>
      <LEVEL_ACTION>
        <COMMENT ref="DRVHighAndTPVIntermediate"/>
      </LEVEL_ACTION>
    </RESULT_COMMENT_RULE>
    <RESULT_COMMENT_RULE>
      <DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITIONS>
        <DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITION>
          <DRUG_NAME>DRV/r</DRUG_NAME>
          <EQ>5</EQ>
        </DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITION>
        <DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITION>
          <DRUG_NAME>TPV/r</DRUG_NAME>
          <EQ>3</EQ>
        </DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITION>
      </DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITIONS>
      <LEVEL_ACTION>
        <COMMENT ref="DRVHighAndTPVLow"/>
      </LEVEL_ACTION>
    </RESULT_COMMENT_RULE>
    <RESULT_COMMENT_RULE>
      <DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITIONS>
        <DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITION>
          <DRUG_NAME>DRV/r</DRUG_NAME>
          <EQ>5</EQ>
        </DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITION>
        <DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITION>
          <DRUG_NAME>TPV/r</DRUG_NAME>
          <EQ>2</EQ>
        </DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITION>
      </DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITIONS>
      <LEVEL_ACTION>
        <COMMENT ref="DRVHighAndTPVPotentialLow"/>
      </LEVEL_ACTION>
    </RESULT_COMMENT_RULE>
    <RESULT_COMMENT_RULE>
      <DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITIONS>
        <DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITION>
          <DRUG_NAME>DRV/r</DRUG_NAME>
          <EQ>5</EQ>
        </DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITION>
        <DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITION>
          <DRUG_NAME>TPV/r</DRUG_NAME>
          <EQ>1</EQ>
        </DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITION>
      </DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITIONS>
      <LEVEL_ACTION>
        <COMMENT ref="DRVHighAndTPVSusceptible"/>
      </LEVEL_ACTION>
    </RESULT_COMMENT_RULE>
    <RESULT_COMMENT_RULE>
      <DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITIONS>
        <DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITION>
          <DRUG_NAME>DRV/r</DRUG_NAME>
          <EQ>4</EQ>
        </DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITION>
      </DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITIONS>
      <LEVEL_ACTION>
        <COMMENT ref="DRVIntermediate"/>
      </LEVEL_ACTION>
    </RESULT_COMMENT_RULE>
    <RESULT_COMMENT_RULE>
      <DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITIONS>
        <DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITION>
          <DRUG_NAME>DRV/r</DRUG_NAME>
          <EQ>3</EQ>
        </DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITION>
      </DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITIONS>
      <LEVEL_ACTION>
        <COMMENT ref="DRVLow"/>
      </LEVEL_ACTION>
    </RESULT_COMMENT_RULE>
    <RESULT_COMMENT_RULE>
      <DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITIONS>
        <DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITION>
          <DRUG_NAME>RPV</DRUG_NAME>
          <EQ>4</EQ>
        </DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITION>
      </DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITIONS>
      <LEVEL_ACTION>
        <COMMENT ref="RPVIntermediate"/>
      </LEVEL_ACTION>
    </RESULT_COMMENT_RULE>
    <RESULT_COMMENT_RULE>
      <DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITIONS>
        <DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITION>
          <DRUG_NAME>RPV</DRUG_NAME>
          <EQ>3</EQ>
        </DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITION>
      </DRUG_LEVEL_CONDITIONS>
      <LEVEL_ACTION>
        <COMMENT ref="RPVLow"/>
      </LEVEL_ACTION>
    </RESULT_COMMENT_RULE>
  </RESULT_COMMENTS>
</ALGORITHM>
